<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The campagne of the French King in the year 1677 In which is described exactly the three sieges and taking in of Valenciennes by assault, and of the town and citadel of Cambray, and of St. Omers, with an account of the Battel of Cassel. Licensed Sept. the 6th, 1678. Roger L'Estrange.</title>
            <title>Campagna del re christianissimo nell' anno 1677. English.</title>
            <author>Primi Fassola di San Maiolo, Giovan Battista Feliciano, conte, 1648-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C399B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203952</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825300</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825300</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29680</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32919)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29680)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1863:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The campagne of the French King in the year 1677 In which is described exactly the three sieges and taking in of Valenciennes by assault, and of the town and citadel of Cambray, and of St. Omers, with an account of the Battel of Cassel. Licensed Sept. the 6th, 1678. Roger L'Estrange.</title>
                  <title>Campagna del re christianissimo nell' anno 1677. English.</title>
                  <author>Primi Fassola di San Maiolo, Giovan Battista Feliciano, conte, 1648-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Dring, at the Harrow at the corner of Chancery-lane in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Primi Fassola di San Maiolo, Giovan Battista Feliciano, conte.  La campagna del re christianissimo nell' anno 1677.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29680:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29680:1"/>
            <p>THE Campagne OF THE FRENCH KING, In the Year 1677.</p>
            <p>In which is deſcribed exactly the three Sieges and taking in of <hi>Valenciennes</hi> by aſſault, and of the Town and Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadel of <hi>Cambray,</hi> and of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> with an account of the Battel of <hi>Caſſel.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Licenſed <hi>Sept.</hi> the 6th, 1678.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for Thomas <hi>Dring,</hi> at the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row at the corner of <hi>Chancery-lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:29680:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29680:2"/>
            <head>THE CAMPAGNE OF THE French King In the Year 1677, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NO ſooner had thoſe puiſſant Parties, who were ingaged in a war, that had divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded almoſt all <hi>Europe,</hi> ſeen the concluſion of the Campagne 1676 and the beginning of the Year 1677, but they began
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29680:3"/>
with equal heat and diligence to put their Armies into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to enter upon action, and to give Life to thoſe Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations on foot, which might be advantagious to them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Eſtate of the Courts of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </note>The Imperialiſts being re-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the Peace made with the Rebells of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the Circles of the Empire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of hopes for the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the War on the other ſide of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> every one for their parts formed very ſtrong Armies. The Spaniards, to ſhew the Vigour of the new Government of <hi>Don John,</hi> ſeemed to cover the Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean with Ships, and all <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talonia</hi> with Soldiers: and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in the low Countrys to expect mighty ſumms for their releif. The Hollanders vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the evil ſucceſs of the laſt Campagne, did not only under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29680:3"/>
to recrute their Troops, but alſo to encreaſe them by new Levies. <hi>France</hi> who alone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding theſe preparations of ſo puiſſant Enemies, was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, but put it ſelf into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to reſiſt all their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. The chance of Arms on the other ſide being againſt the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> the King of the Sweeds at the head of his victorious Army thought of nothing elſe but of reconque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoſe places which they had taken from him.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Aſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at <hi>Nimegen</hi> for the general Peace came together ſlowly, and though the Ambaſſadors from all parties had waited on his Majeſty the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who was choſen for a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, it might be eaſily judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that for the moſt part thoſe Princes who had ſent them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29680:4"/>
had ſeveral Intereſts in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Voyage of <hi>Flanders</hi> reſolved on.</note>Things being in this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, after the French King had order'd a conſiderable part of his Armies for the <hi>Rhine,</hi> for <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and for <hi>Sicily,</hi> he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med out of the Troops that were left a flouriſhing army for <hi>Flanders,</hi> and reſolved to command it himſelf in perſon. He declared at the ſame time the general Officers which he had choſen to ſerve him in the ſeveral Provinces.<note place="margin">The names of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of the French Army.</note> He gave to Marſhal <hi>Crequi</hi> the command of the Armie in <hi>Germany.</hi> To the Marſhal Duke <hi>de Navailes</hi> that of the Army of <hi>Catalonia.</hi> The Marſhal Duke <hi>de Vivonne</hi> was continued in <hi>Sicily.</hi> And the Marſhal <hi>de Humieres, de Schomberg</hi> and <hi>Luxemburg, Feuillade</hi> and <hi>Lorges</hi> were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated to Command in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29680:4"/>
under the Kings Orders.</p>
            <p>The reſolution of the French Kings departure was publiſhed on the 25th of <hi>February,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Kings reſolution ſurpriſes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very body.</note> and equally ſurpriſed both the Court, the Officers of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies French and Strangers. The Seaſon ſo little proper for Military Actions, the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne unfurniſhed of Forrage, the Feaſts and divertiſements, which the King had made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, to hide his ſecret deſigns, had deceived them all. He had no Equipage ready and yet he muſt have it, and would depart within three days.</p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi> Governour of the Spaniſh <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chiefly the Duke</hi> De Villa Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſa.</note> ſeeing ſo great plenty of Forrage and proviſion which they had made on the Frontiers, did not amuſe himſelf with the rigours of the Winter, and not at all doubting but that the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29680:5"/>
French were about to come thundering down upon him all on a ſudden, he aforehand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enforced his Gariſons, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided what was neceſſary in all places which he was able to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, and which he thought lay moſt in danger of Siege. He alſo employed with great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry and indefatigable care and pains thoſe Summs of Mony which they had remitted him out of <hi>Spain</hi> to put his Troops in good condition, and he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly preſſed the Hollanders to joyn themſelves with him, that they might joyntly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe what ever the French ſhould go about to enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The French Kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture.</note>The Sunday Morning being 18th of <hi>February,</hi> the King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts from the Caſtle of St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi> where he left the Queen and Monſieur the <hi>Dauphin:</hi> The moſt parts of the Princes,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29680:5"/>
Dukes and Lords of the Court following him, in the quality of Volunteers. The ſame day he arrived in <hi>Champaine,</hi> the firſt of <hi>March</hi> he lay at <hi>Chau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> the ſecond at St. <hi>Quintin,</hi> the third at <hi>Cate-cambreſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arrives at Valencie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> and the fourth he came to the Camp before <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> before the Equipage was arrived there: and then it was that he firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to diſcover a part of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions.</p>
            <p>The French King the laſt year had laid the foundation of the Enterpriſes, which he ſince ſo gloriouſly atchieved. Thoſe who did not penetrate into the buſineſs of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Conde</hi> and <hi>Bouchain,</hi> and who condemned the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours which had been made on <hi>Flanders,</hi> becauſe they believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it more neceſſary to conſerve our Frontiers on the ſide of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29680:6"/>
               <hi>Rhine,</hi> now were able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive die weakneſs of their reaſoning. For indeed theſe two places did incommode thoſe of <hi>Hanault</hi> and <hi>Cambreſis</hi> and hindred them from all kind of communication: the Baron of <hi>Quincy</hi> with a flying Camp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing them to extremity. He being a native of the Country, knew perfectly all the Coaſt, and underſtanding War ſo well as he did, he not only hindred all commerce between thoſe places, but ſo oppoſed thoſe Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards on that ſide, that they were not able to make any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roads into <hi>Picardy,</hi> nor receive thoſe contributions they had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed there; nor ſubſiſt in their Gariſons without much trouble. Theſe courſes of the Baron of <hi>Quincy,</hi> and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazins which they had made on the Frontiers in divers places
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29680:6"/>
ſhewed plain enough the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns that <hi>France</hi> might have upon <hi>Mons, Valenciennes,</hi> St. <hi>Guilain,</hi> and <hi>Cambray;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, <hi>Ypres</hi> and St. <hi>Omer</hi> being alſo menaced by the grand pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations of Arms and Munition which they made on the ſide of <hi>Artois</hi> and of <hi>Boulonois,</hi> it was difficult to judge the true inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the French, and they never imagined that they would enterpriſe more than one Siege at one time.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Marquis de Louvois</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of State,<note place="margin">The activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Marquis de Louvois.</hi>
               </note> and chief mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter for the carrying on of the War, had ſo ably managed all things to forward the deſigns of the King, and had joyned to his Counſels ſo much care and pains, made voyages, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven orders ſo to the purpoſe, that aſſoon as his Majeſty arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Camp, all things
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29680:7"/>
were in readineſs to begin the Campagne.</p>
            <p>The Marſhal the Duke of <hi>Luxembourg,</hi> who was depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Court with this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſome daies before the King, had inverted <hi>Valencien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> the twenty eighth of <hi>Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> and the better to hide the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Siege, the Marſhal <hi>de Humieres</hi> held <hi>Mons</hi> blocked up at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Siege.</note>The King immediately cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lines to be drawn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, viſited the Poſts, view'd the Place, and gave all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry orders for the ſhutting up the paſſages to hinder them from all manner of ſuccour. The Camp encreaſed immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately by the arrival of ſeveral Troops and their Equipages, and by the proviſions which were continually brought thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Magazins, where
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29680:7"/>
they had been ſtored up: So that within the ſpace of eight daies there were no leſs than 50000 Combatants, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed appeared an incredible thing, conſidering the rigour of the ſeaſon, and the ill condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they might expect to find themſelves in, where a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try was deſolate by the War. In the mean time Monſieur <hi>Le Mot</hi> Marſhal <hi>de</hi> Camp, and Monſieur <hi>de Mommont</hi> Brigadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Infantry with theſe Troops which they comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, did incommodate St. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> in <hi>Artois</hi> and gave a jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to <hi>Ypres.</hi> The Baron <hi>de Quincy</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp</hi> and Monſieur <hi>de Fitte</hi> Brigadier of the Cavalry were at the Gates of <hi>Cambray.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> The groſs of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being come into the Camp, the King diſtributed their Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. He took his own neer to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29680:8"/>
               <hi>Famars,</hi> which was on that ſide where they made the Attacques, and he choſe the Marſhal <hi>de Humieres</hi> and <hi>Feuillade</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand under his orders. The Duke of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> had his Quarter at <hi>Launoy.</hi> The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal <hi>de Lorges</hi> at Mount <hi>Azin.</hi> Theſe Poſts were in ſo many Villages ſituate on thee eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies the moſt neer to the place.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſtrength of the place.</note>
               <hi>Valenciennes</hi> is a place ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, that it may well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all theſe grand preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an Army royal for the taking it. Its ſituation is very advantageous, and the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Valentinian</hi> found it ſo well fortified for defence that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on it his Name. It's al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo conſiderable for the people which inhabit it, for its great commerce and for the reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it has had for having reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great Armies. Beſides its
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29680:8"/>
fortifications it is encompaſſed about with two Rivers, the <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caut,</hi> and the <hi>Ronnel,</hi> with an inacceſſible marſh, and Sluces to drown all the country round about it. In fine, it is one of the moſt important places not only of <hi>Hanault,</hi> but of all the low Countries. Beſides, the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it ſecures a part of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardy</hi> and of <hi>Champaine</hi> and the Countries of the French Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, takes away from <hi>Cambray</hi> all hopes of ſuccours, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances the bounds of <hi>France</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into the heart of <hi>Flanders.</hi> All theſe thing being well known to the Spaniards as well as to the French, they forgot nothing which might ſerve to ſave <hi>Valenciennes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi> endeavours its defence.</note> The Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi> had ſent away this Commiſſary General to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Dendermond</hi> with money to furniſh the Magazins for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29680:9"/>
the ſubſiſtence of his Army, and for the furthering the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the Hollanders, who aſſembled together about <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſendal</hi> with a deſign to march a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the French.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Gariſon there.</note>They had in the place a 1000 Horſe, an Italian Regiment of Foot commanded by <hi>Silva.</hi> Two Regiments of Walloons, one commanded by the Count <hi>de Solres,</hi> the other by Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Oſtils</hi> ſometimes Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Conde.</hi> Two Regiments of Germans of the <hi>Marquis</hi> of <hi>Ledens,</hi> and 2000 ſelect Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſes; to whom they had given Arms and Officers able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them. It was abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furniſhed with Artillery, and with all ſorts of munition for War and proviſion for men: and a great many both of the Nobility and of the country Payſants had put themſelves
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29680:9"/>
within it for its defence. The Count <hi>de Solres</hi> being it ſeems abroad when it was inveſted, was fain to uſe his skill to enter again. The <hi>Marquis de Richebou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Brother to the Prince of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinoy</hi> a man of Experience and Courage commanded there in quality of Governour. He had inſpired both the Soldiers and the Inhabitants with a ſtrong reſolution to defend themſelves to the very laſt extremity, and had cauſed Gallouſes to be ſet up in the croſs Streets to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the people that they might be no hindrance to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and might not dare to ſpread any Intelligence that might cauſe any mutiny, and in fine, he had ſo well diſpoſed the Gariſon without and the <hi>Militia</hi> within, that he might promiſe to himſelf a vigorous defence. All this they came to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29680:10"/>
underſtand by an Italian Officer of the Gariſon who was taken in the Camp.</p>
            <p>The continual Rains had ſtopped the Canon on the way, and hindred the King that he could not give order for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the Trenches. But on the eighth, they being come, he deferred it no longer; and gave order to attaque it in the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt places, which appeared to be at the Port of <hi>Cambray</hi> and that of <hi>Cardon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Attaque reſolved.</note> but the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of bringing thither their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non made him reſolve to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the attaque to be made on the ſide of the Port of <hi>Azin,</hi> although the better fortified. To this end they muſt firſt take a Crown Work,<note place="margin">The Horn work de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</note> defended by two Demy-Baſtions with their Halfmoons advanced and with a ſtrong Paliſado, a large ditch, and a good Counterſcarp. But
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29680:10"/>
beſides all this there was a well furniſhed Halfmoon, which had Works on Front and a great ditch betwixt two others, and a little before it an irregular Fort named the <hi>Pie</hi> or the <hi>Horſhooe,</hi> to which one Arm of the <hi>Eſcaut</hi> ſerv'd for a ditch. They muſt croſs over the <hi>Eſcaut</hi> which ran with great rapidneſs along the ramparts of the Town, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate by a little Fort. In ſpite of all theſe obſtacles which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared not to be ſurmounted, they believed if they might be able once to render themſelves maſters of this Crown-work, then to prepare their Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and place their Morterpie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to fire the body of the Town, that they would be obliged to capitulate rather than to ſee it reduced to aſhes without coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King any thing but pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. So then his Majeſty gave
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29680:11"/>
orders for the opening the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches on the ninth or tenth of <hi>March,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The opening of the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> and would needs aſſiſt in it himſelf to animate his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers by his preſence.</p>
            <p>The Marſhall <hi>Schomberg</hi> was the firſt that mounted the Guard with Count <hi>Bardi Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golotti</hi> Lieutenant General,<note place="margin">The ground of M. <hi>Schom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg.</hi>
               </note> the Count of St. <hi>Geran</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Marquis <hi>de Angeau Ayde de Camp,</hi> three Battalions of the Regiment of Guards of <hi>Picardy</hi> and <hi>Soiſſons:</hi> followed by Monſier <hi>Javil</hi> Brigadier of the Cavalry with ſix Squadrons, two of the Companies of the <hi>Corps du Guard</hi> of <hi>Noailles</hi> and <hi>Duras,</hi> one of the <hi>Gens de Arms</hi> of Scotch and Engliſh: and the others of the Collonel General maſter <hi>de Camp</hi> and of the Kings. This laſt Body conſiſted of two thouſand Soldiers drawn out of divers Regiments, who
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29680:11"/>
carried the Trench above ſix hundred paces towards the Counterſcarp. The beſieged fail'd not to fire ſtoutly, but with little effect, for there was but a few Soldiers and two Officers killed. The Marquis of <hi>Livourn</hi> had his Horſe killed under him by a Canon ſhot as he went to viſit a certain Poſt.<note place="margin">The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is wounded.</note> The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Richbourg</hi> Governour of the place, being advanced to the out Works was wounded that night in giving out orders, and his wound putting him in a condition not to act, Monſieur <hi>Deſpres</hi> was put in his place, with full and abſolute power by the conſent of all the Officers: this was not then known in the Camp.</p>
            <p>From the tenth to the twelfth at night they put a Blind at the head of the Trench,<note place="margin">The Guard of M. <hi>de Feuillade.</hi>
               </note> and made a place for their Arms. The
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29680:12"/>
Marſhal <hi>de Feuillade</hi> was that day with the Marquis <hi>de Renel</hi> Lieutenant general, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>de Tilladet</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Prince <hi>de Harcourt</hi> Aid <hi>de Camp</hi> at the head of two Battalions of the Guards of Switzers, two of <hi>Navarre,</hi> one of <hi>Harcourt-Beuvron,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Artois</hi> under Monſieur <hi>de Aubarede</hi> Brigadier of the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſuſtained by the Marquis <hi>de Revel</hi> Brigadier of the Cavalry at the head of the Squadrons of the <hi>Corps du Guard</hi> of <hi>Luxembourg</hi> and <hi>Lorges,</hi> of the <hi>Gend'armery</hi> of the Collonel Maſter of the Camp and the Regiment of the King.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Guard of M. <hi>de Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg.</hi>
               </note>At the beginning of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh night the King went himſels to ſee the Guard moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Marſhal <hi>Luxembourg,</hi> the Marquis <hi>de Cardonnierre</hi> Lieutenant General, the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29680:12"/>
               <hi>de Sourdis,</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Bartillade</hi> Brigadier of the Cavalry, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Tracy</hi> Brigadier of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry, the Marquis <hi>de Chiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> Aid <hi>de Camp,</hi> with the three laſt Battalons of the Guards, and the two of <hi>Auvergne</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Marquis <hi>de Coeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vres,</hi> one <hi>Lemayn,</hi> and the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of the <hi>Corps du Guard</hi> of <hi>Nailles</hi> and <hi>Duras,</hi> one <hi>Gens d' Arms</hi> and the others of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel maſter <hi>de Camp</hi> and of the King.</p>
            <p>On the morrow being the twelfth,<note place="margin">The Battery.</note> the Artillery began to play. Monſieur <hi>de Vauban</hi> who had the direction of the Works made them to continue a Demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſap to favour the Canon, whilſt the firſt ſhots diſmounted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pieces of the beſieged. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur St. <hi>Cathern</hi> Commiſſary of the Artillery was killed in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29680:13"/>
Battery where he commanded The proviſions which they had made on the Frontier,<note place="margin">Proviſions in the Camp.</note> for the ſubſiſtence of the Army arrived by <hi>Bouchain</hi> and <hi>Conde</hi> and made plenty in the Camp.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Monſieur arrives.</note>Monſieur the only Brother of the King who had left <hi>Paris</hi> the ſeventh, arrived at the Camp this day and was lodged in the King's Quarter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">M. <hi>de Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis</hi> his Guard.</note>The Marſhal <hi>de Lorges</hi> moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Trenches with Count <hi>Pleſſis</hi> Lieutenant general, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier <hi>de Albert</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> Marquis <hi>de Livourn</hi> Brigadier of the Cavalry, the Marquis of <hi>Cavois</hi> Aid <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Bourlemount</hi> Brigadier of the Infantry with three Battali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Kings Regiment, two of the Royal and one other of <hi>Freezelier</hi> aſſiſted by two Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of the Guards <hi>du Corps</hi> of <hi>Luxembourg</hi> and <hi>Lorges,</hi> one of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29680:13"/>
the <hi>Gend' Arms,</hi> and the others of the Curaſſiers of <hi>Sourdis</hi> and <hi>Tilladet.</hi> They approached neer the French on the edge of the Counterſcarp, and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>de Sevigni</hi> Enſign of the <hi>Dauphins Gend' Arms</hi> was there wounded. They ſeized on ſome Spaniſh Officers in the Camp, who would have entred the place either to carry them ſome intelligence or to have joyned themſelves to their Companies.</p>
            <p>The ſame night they took one Redout and the <hi>Fauxbourg No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtredame</hi> without much reſiſtance on the beſiegeds part.<note place="margin">They take the <hi>Faux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtredame.</hi>
               </note> As more than thirty pieces of Canon, a great many Morterpieces, and of Bombes pour'd down upon the Town, a continual tempeſt of Fire, Lead and Iron, one would have thought that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged had enough to do within the place and that they had not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29680:14"/>
time to think of ſuccouring them without. But there was yet a reaſon for their ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, which was that they hoped to be able to drown the Beſiegers in the ſame places without, when they ſhould ſeize them, in letting go their Sluces, and ſo revenge by water the ravage they had made by Fire. They then let them looſe in the <hi>Fauxbourg,</hi> but to little purpoſe, for there the fifth part of the Guard did not quit the place but lodg'd themſelves there, and made many places of ſhelter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Defences and Paliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does were overthrown by the Artillery.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">M. <hi>de Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mieres</hi> Guard,</note>It was the Marſhal <hi>De Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mieres</hi> who mounted the fifth Guard on the thirteenth with the Count <hi>de Auvergne</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General, the Chevalier <hi>de Tilladet,</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29680:14"/>
the Chevalier <hi>Nogent Ayde de Camp,</hi> the Chevalier <hi>Grignan</hi> Brigadier of the Cavalry, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur St. <hi>George</hi> Brigadier of the Infantry, two Battalions of the Regiment of <hi>Lyonnois,</hi> two of the <hi>Dauphins,</hi> one of <hi>Harcour Bauvron,</hi> one of <hi>Fuziliers,</hi> and the Squadrons of one quarter of the <hi>Gens d' Armes,</hi> and the light Horſe of the Guards, one of the firſt Companies of the white Muſqueteers, one of the <hi>Dauphins Gens d' Arms,</hi> one of the Cuiraſſiers, and the other of <hi>Tilladet</hi> and <hi>Sourdis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourteenth the Guard was relieved by the Marſhal <hi>de Schomberg,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> de Scombergs <hi>Guard.</hi>
               </note> the Duke <hi>de Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy</hi> Lieutenant General, the Prince Palatin <hi>de Birckenfeild</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Marquis <hi>de Montrevel</hi> Brigadier of the Cavalry, the Marquis <hi>Pierre</hi> Brigadier of the Infantry, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29680:15"/>
the Marquis <hi>de Arcy Ayde de Camp</hi> with two Battalions of the Queens Regiment, two of the Fleets, one of <hi>Piemont Genoways,</hi> and one alſo of <hi>Saluces</hi> of <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> and thoſe Troops which the Court of <hi>Savoy</hi> ſent for <hi>France,</hi> and ſeven Squadrons of the ſecond company of black Muſqueteers, the <hi>Dauphins</hi> light Horſe, the <hi>Gend' Arms</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jou,</hi> and the Cuiraſſiers of <hi>Sour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> of <hi>Tilladet,</hi> and of <hi>Bartil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> de Feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>illades Guard.</note>The Guard was mounted the fifteenth by the Duke of <hi>Feuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade,</hi> the Count <hi>Montbron</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General, Monſieur <hi>Stoup</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Prince <hi>de Elbeuf</hi> Ayd <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Marquis <hi>de Revel</hi> Brigadier of of the Cavalry, the Marquis <hi>de Uxelles</hi> Brigadier of the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, with ſix Battalions of the Regiments of <hi>Alſatia, Saluces</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29680:15"/>
               <hi>Salis,</hi> and ſix Squadrons of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillat, Grignan, Leomare, Koniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and <hi>Gaſſion.</hi> This day the Works were very much advan- and divided into three branches, being more than two 200 yards in length, and two in height. They being fortified in very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, and encompaſſing the Angle of the Crown Work which we deſcribed before, gave ſhelter to moſt of the Infantry, and favoured the approach of the Batteries.</p>
            <p>All that we have told you was done by the Kings orders, which he gave forth himſelf every day. He was every where he commanded, he animated the Officers and Soldiers with his preſence, and was with them often on the leaſt occaſion.</p>
            <p>The ſixteenth the Marſhal <hi>de Luxembourg</hi> mounted the Trench with the Marquis <hi>de</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> de Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgs <hi>Guard.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:29680:16"/>
               <hi>Trouſſe</hi> Lieutenant General, the Count St. <hi>Geran</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Chevalier <hi>de Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſme</hi> Ayd <hi>de Camp,</hi> and three Battalions of the French Guards conducted by Monſieur <hi>de Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentel</hi> Brigadier of the Infantry and Captain in the Regiment, and three other Battalions of <hi>Picardy</hi> and of <hi>Soiſſons</hi> under the Marquis of <hi>Boulemont</hi> and <hi>le Pierre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this while the Beſiegers loſt but very few men, and the beſieged did not ſhew all that vigour that they expected. Whether it were that the Trench was ſo good that it ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred unprofitable the ſhot of the Beſieged, or that they were ſo expoſed to the Batteries that it was impoſſible to fire ſtoutly from the Redouts: or that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they did not think that little Fort important enough for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29680:16"/>
to hazard their Soldiers, which they might be willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve for the defence of the Town. For at laſt when they ſhould have loſt that Poſt, the River which ſeparated it from the Town, gave ſhelter enough to that ſide, and two other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the marſh and the Water Sluces which they having let looſe, hindred well enough their approaches, ſo that they did not fear any aſſault.</p>
            <p>The King whom ſucceſs ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated,<note place="margin">The King attaques the Crown works.</note> and who meaſured his deſigns by the progreſs of the Siege, reſolved to attaque the Counterſcarp on the morrow being the ſeventeenth. He vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited the Poſts that night, he wrot with his own hand the orders of that attaque, and put them into the hand of Monſieur <hi>Roſe</hi> Secretaty of the Cabinet to coppy them forth, which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29680:17"/>
were diſtributed preſently to the General Officers whoſe day it was, and to the principal offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Troops deſigned for that enterpriſe. His Majeſty commanded ſixty of the Guard of the Body to a light in the <hi>Fauxbourg</hi> armed with their Carabines, and to obſerve all the night the countenance of the Beſieged. He cauſed to be made ready in the ſame <hi>Fauxbourg Noſtredame</hi> a Battery of ſix pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ordinance, and ſome Mortars which might annoy the backſide of the Crown Work. The Troops which he had choſen for this enterpriſe, beſide thoſe which were already on the Guard in the Trenches were the two Companies of white Muſqueteers command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Chevalier <hi>Fourbin,</hi> and the black by Monſieur <hi>Jau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel,</hi> Captain Lieutenants, the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29680:17"/>
Company of Granadiers of his Houſe under Captains <hi>Riotot,</hi> and twenty four Companies of Granadiers drawn out of all the Battalions of the Army. All theſe Troops went into the Trench the ſixteenth at night. The Granadiers of the Kings Regiments lodg'd amongſt the white Muſqueteers, and the Guards and the Granadiers of <hi>Avergne</hi> and <hi>Navarre,</hi> among the black Muſqueteers, and the Battalion of <hi>Burlemont,</hi> the Marquis <hi>de Angeau</hi> the the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of Aid <hi>de Camp.</hi> The Chevalier <hi>de Vendôme</hi> would not be relieved on this impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant occaſion, for Which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared himſelf, and obained leave to fight, and the Marquis <hi>de Angeau</hi> carried him orders from the King to obſerve exactly all things that ſhould paſs in that action, that he might be able
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29680:18"/>
to ſend the news with ſpeed to his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The order of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taque.</note>All things being thus diſpoſed for the Attaque, on the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth in the morning about nine or ten of the clock there was heard nine ſhots of Canon, which was a ſign for the Beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to come forth of the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to attaque the Crown Work.</p>
            <p>The King being ready on the bank of the River, and the report of his preſence being ſpread tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the commanded Troops, they prepared themſelves for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the enterpriſe with an incredible order and undaunted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The Granadiers of the Kings houſe back'd by the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>Fourbin</hi> at the head of the white Muſqueteers and by <hi>Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelle</hi> and <hi>Davejan</hi> Captains of the Guards, with one of their Battalions aſſaulted the right ſide
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29680:18"/>
of the Work, the Granadiers of the Regiment of <hi>Picardy</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by <hi>Jauvelle</hi> with the black Muſqueteers and by the Marquis of <hi>Bourlemont,</hi> with a part of the Regiment af <hi>Picardy</hi> aſſaulted the left ſide, and the Marquis <hi>de Trouſſe</hi> Lieutenant General, and the Count St. <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> with the reſt of the Regiment of <hi>Picardy,</hi> and the commanded Troops, fell upon the Front.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſpres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The beſieged vanquiſhed.</note> the Count <hi>Solres</hi> and the other Officers of the place, Who were aſſembled in the ſame Work to conſult of the means to defend it, hearing all on a ſudden the ſhot of the Canon after a great calm and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found ſilence on either ſide for ſome time, and perceiving the Troops of the King to advance, they immediately ſeparated and ran to the places where they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29680:19"/>
were about to make the Attaques and there to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate their men to do well. But their Soldiers being terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Artillery, expoſed to the ſhot of the Carabines in the <hi>Fauxbourg</hi> and to the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Tempeſt of the Bombs, and gall'd in the flank, their half moons on the ſides not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to help them, they gave themſelves for loſt, and that the aſſailants, which on every ſide encompaſſed them about, would throw down Heaven upon them. Fear having ſeiz'd upon them, they abandoned all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, Counterſcarp, Palliſſadoes, Ditch, and the Work it ſelf, which they ſhould have defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and their Arms alſo: and in the end their courage wholly forſaking them, they caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a croud and without Order or Rank fled out of the well
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29680:19"/>
furniſhed half Moon.<note place="margin">The Valour of the aſſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants.</note> The Muſqueteers and the Granadiers mingling themſelves with thoſe who fled, ſtop'd them in the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of their retreat, and killed all thoſe they encounter'd on the way. But thoſe of the French party who had pierced even into the half Moon by a wooden Bridg, which was laid over the Ditch, perceived that to favour the retreat of the Beſieged, they had let down the draw-Bridg which gave entranee into the <hi>Pie:</hi> but for that the wicket was barricadoed with dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the wounded, and the croud of thoſe who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſave themſelves not being able to do it all at once, flung themſelves into the Arm of the River which ſerved the ditch of the <hi>Pie,</hi> others lay down on the ground counterfeiting themſelves dead, to avoid that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29680:20"/>
way the firſt fury of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querers. This diſorder of the Beſieged animated the moſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the French, and gave them no leiſure to make any reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of any Ambuſcade which they might have laid for them, or of the reſiſtance which they might find, they puſh'd on their victory to the end, and carried on by a point of honour ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate among thoſe Muſqueteers, of which none would yield to his companion the glory of being the firſt in thoſe ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous occaſions, ſo that they flung themſelves one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thorow the Wicket. It had been no hard matter for a few Officers and Soldiers which were in the <hi>Pie,</hi> to repreſs the ardour of the moſt furious: But whether they could no longer diſtinguiſh Foes from Friends, or that they were of the number
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29680:20"/>
of thoſe that fled the vigour with which they ſaw themſelves pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, had made them utterly loſe their judgement and their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, they flung down their Arms, and ſome of them who were afraid of falling by the edge of the Sword demanded their lives on their knees. The Conquerors advanced towards the Gate of the Town, but they found the draw-Bridge up. They were aware that on the left ſide of the entry of the <hi>Pie,</hi> there was a litle ladder placed in the wall, which ſerved as a cruſt to the <hi>Pie,</hi> by which one might aſcend upon the Terrace that cover'd it, and from thence paſs to the rampart of the Town by the means of certain vaults which reached from the ſide of a little Sluce-houſe, to the place of the draw-Bridge.</p>
            <p>The Granadiers enforcing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29680:21"/>
then a little Port which ſhut up that ladder,<note place="margin">They get in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Town.</note> they mounted upon the Terrace, where they found but two or three Soldiers, and paſſing the Terrace upon the vaults which were faſtned there, they went on even to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſmall Gate, which gave entrance to the Rampart. From thence they advanced to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the draw-Bridg, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving chaſed away certain Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers who guarded it, they got down to give a free paſſage to their companions, and they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced all together into the firſt Street even in ſight of the ſtone Bridg over the <hi>Eſcaut</hi> which croſt the Town in that place.</p>
            <p>The Muſqueteers and the Granadiers who were advanced into the Town under <hi>Vinche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guerre,</hi> and followed by <hi>Moiſſac,</hi> and <hi>le Barre</hi> chief Officers, and under <hi>Molinneuf</hi> Lieutenant of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29680:21"/>
the others, ſeconded by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Beaumont</hi> Volunteer, not being above thirty men in all, when they perceived the people running to their Arms, and ſaw a party of the Cavalry who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to rank themſelves upon the ſtone Bridge, they at firſt thought good to ſhelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the porches of the houſes. But their number pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, increaſed by the arrival of ſome under <hi>Maupertuis,</hi> yet by reaſon the little door of the <hi>Pie</hi> by which they muſt paſs, was troubleſome, there could come but a few at once, they fortified themſelves as well as they could in the ſame Street, and there ſtood firm for ſome time. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Cavaliers and Dragoons of the Enemy and ſome Soldiers alſo advanced ſtill on this ſide the Bridge to drive them back, but the moſt forward of them
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:29680:22"/>
being kill'd, their Cavalry left the Bridge to put themſelves in Battel aray in the grand place. The <hi>Militia,</hi> who had run to their Arms on the report being ſpread of the entry of the Enemy, were ſurpriſed, yet made a ſhow as if they would diſpute the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Bridg, and to make faſt the chains croſs the Streets. But the Chevalier <hi>Fourbin, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velle, Riotot,</hi> with the reſt of their companies, and all thoſe who had been willing to follow having wholly defeated or taken priſoners all that withſtood them without, and having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaged the Baſcule or hanging door they entred the Town like a Torrent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Town taken by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault.</note>The principal Burgers at the firſt brute of the Entry of the French into the Town ran to the Alarum bell at the Council houſe and made their deputies
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29680:22"/>
to come forth to the Troops which were already in <hi>Battalia</hi> and to tell them that they would capitulate. But <hi>Moiſſac</hi> and the other Officers told them that it was not time now, and that it was not the Cuſtom that they ſhould capitulate with their Maſters. Then one of the Deputies deſired at leaſt that they would let them go to implore the Clemency of the King, which they permitted them, who meeting the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> at the gate of the Town, accompanied with Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Dumetz</hi> Leiutenant General of the Artillery,<note place="margin">Hoſtages ſent to the King.</note> he put them into the hands of the Marquis <hi>de Angeau,</hi> for to conduct them to his Majeſty. He then commanded the Muſqueteers to ſtand in <hi>Battalia</hi> in the grand Place, and their Officers made thoſe of the Gariſon whom they found there, to lay down their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29680:23"/>
Arms and thoſe of the Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to diſmount. He ordered the Granadiers to ſeiſe the Market place, where was a ſmall Court of Guard of the Enemies, and diſpoſed of the reſt of the Troops and of the Artillery as he thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to aſſure himſelf of all quarters of the Twon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The King can hardly beleive the Report.</note>This great Action was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with ſo much rapidity and was accompanied with ſo much Valour and good Fortune, that the King who had only order'd the taking of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſcarp could very hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive the teſtimony of his own Ears when he heard the Cry of <hi>Vive le Roy,</hi> and the noiſe of their Granadoes and muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets in the middle of the Town. But the Chevalier <hi>de Vandome</hi> who among the firſt had enter'd this placed poſting
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29680:23"/>
with all diligence to his Majeſty, drew him out of his incertitude, and he was no ſooner aſſured of the verity but he went to the place of the Attaque, and met in the way the Baron of <hi>Langia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> and preſently after many other perſons of quality, who confirm'd that they were maſters of the Town. At this certain News the King ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Marquis <hi>De Louvis</hi> to hinder the pillage of the Town and other Deſolations of Conqueſt made by Aſſault,<note place="margin">Marquis <hi>Louvis</hi> ſent into the Town.</note> and to give Orders as he ſhould judge neceſſary, and according as he ſhould find the diſpoſition of things. His Majeſty was but juſt paſt the Bridg which he had lay'd over the <hi>Eſcaut</hi> for Communication of his Quarters, when he met with the Marquis <hi>de Angeau</hi> who conducted the Provoſt of the County of <hi>Hanault</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:29680:24"/>
and the chief of the Inhabitants which they had ſent for Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. They Implored the Clemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the King, and demanded a Confirmation of their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. By the right of war the Town ought to be left to be pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laged by the ſoldiers, which the King let theſe hoſtages know,<note place="margin">The Kings Clemency.</note> yet ſuch was the natural bounty and ſweetneſs of his Majeſty, which equalled his Valour, that he compaſſionated the miſery of the People, and made his Victory and Force to give way to his Generoſity, and would not permit the leaſt diſpleaſure to be done to the Inhabitants, and made them to hope in his mercy.</p>
            <p>The Marquis <hi>de Louvis</hi> being arrived in the Town bid the Muſqueteers to mount on the horſes of the Gariſon which appertained to them of right,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29680:24"/>
and commanded the vanquiſh'd to withdraw themſelves into a Church, till they ſhould receive new orders. Certain ſquadrons of the Guards of the Body and certain Batalions of the French Guards relieved the Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers and the Granadiers: And thus <hi>Valenciennes</hi> by one only aſſault as ſudden as unheard of ſubmitted it ſelf to <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Town obliged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to pay the ſum of 400000 Crowns in acknowledgment of the grace which the King had done them in conſerving their goods,<note place="margin">The Town ranſom'd.</note> the honour of their wives and their Lives, and for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Town from fire and pillage. Eight hundred ſouldiers of the Gariſon ſtay'd upon the place,<note place="margin">The Gariſon made priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of war.</note> all the reſt were made priſoners of war. The principal Officers were the Marquis of <hi>Richboury</hi> Governour of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29680:25"/>
place who was wounded at the beginning of the Seige, <hi>Deſpres</hi> who was ſubſtituted in his place and alſo wounded. The Count <hi>de Solres.</hi> The Marquis <hi>de Leu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The loſſe of the French.</note> 
               <hi>Taxis. Montigni,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>On the French ſide the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>Bourlemonnt</hi> Brigadier of the Infantry maſter <hi>de Camp</hi> of the Regiment of <hi>Picardy</hi> was kill'd. He was a young Officer of great merit, and of very great hopes, he was but newly cured of thoſe wounds which he had received in another occaſion in which he had behaved himſelf very gallantly. They loſt alſo three Captains of foot and one of Horſe, ſeven inferior Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, eleven Muſqueteers and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fifty ſoldiers from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Siege. The Duke of <hi>Luxembourg</hi> and the Count St. <hi>Geran</hi> were ſlightly wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the attaque with ſome
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29680:25"/>
pieces of Granadoes, the others that were wounded were <hi>Champigny, Ferraut,</hi> and ſeveral Officers of the Regiments of Guards. <hi>Cailleres</hi> Captain of that of <hi>Navarre,</hi> the Marquis <hi>de Charmel</hi> Voluntier, about twenty five Muſqueteers and thirty Soldiers more.</p>
            <p>The King viſited the fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,<note place="margin">The King viſits the Fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> and deſigned the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a Citadel with the 40000 Crowns which was impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Town: and for that the place was of that Importance as to require a perſon of an appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Fidelity, great Courage, and deep Prudence to be entru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the Government; his Majeſty choſe the Count <hi>Bardi Magalotta</hi> a Florentine by Birth, but more than thirty years in the French Service, in which time having paſſed through the employs of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29680:26"/>
of Lieutenant, of Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, of the Regiment of the French Guards, of Maſter of the Camp of a Regiment of Italian Foot, he was come to be Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General. The Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy for the King was given to Monſieur <hi>Foucaut</hi> Lieutenant Collonel of the Regiment of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and the Majoralty to Monſieur <hi>de Chazerat</hi> Captain in that of <hi>Navarre.</hi> The Baron <hi>de Quincy</hi> in recompence of thoſe ſervices which he had done, and which he ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to perform before <hi>Cambray,</hi> was made Provoſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that is to ſay, chief of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Praiſes pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly and recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</note>The King publickly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Officers and Voluntiers, who had ſignalized themſelves on this occaſion. He recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed <hi>Jauvelle</hi> Captain Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the black Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29680:26"/>
with a Commiſſion that made him Marſhal <hi>de Camp.</hi> The Marquis <hi>de Vains</hi> Captain Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the ſame Company with Commiſſion and pay of Brigadier of the Cavalry, <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertuis</hi> under Captain Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the white Muſqueteers had the like. <hi>Hoguete, Barrieri, Rigoville,</hi> and <hi>Moiſſac,</hi> Cornets of thoſe two Companies had commiſſions and pay of Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels of Horſe. The Marſhals of <hi>Logis</hi> had their Brevets and appointments of Captains of the light Horſe, and alſo all the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Muſqueteers were recompenſed either with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney or with commiſſions of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or nobleneſs: Monſieur <hi>Vauban</hi> had the gratification of 25000 Crowns. His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ordered to the Duke of <hi>Lude</hi> grand maſter of the Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery to be divided among his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29680:27"/>
and Soldiers 3000 piſtols to heal their wounds. He made mony to be diſtributed among the Troops, and particularly to thoſe Soldiers who had taken priſoners. He gave the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Picardy</hi> to the Marquis of <hi>Harcourt-Beuron,</hi> and that of <hi>Harcourt-Beuron</hi> to the Marquis <hi>de Humieres</hi> Son of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rejoycing at <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </note>The news of taking this place was carried the eighteenth to the Queen at <hi>Paris,</hi> who had been there ſince the fourth with the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> which gave them great joy and cauſed rejoycings thorow that great City. The <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung in the Church of <hi>Noſtre Dame.</hi> The Queen aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted there with Monſieur the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> and were accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all the Princes and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of the Blood, and all the Nobility, the Archbiſhop, Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29680:27"/>
Parliament, Magiſtrates, Ambaſſadours, and Miniſters, Strangers. At night there were bonfires made thorow all the Streets.<note place="margin">The Queen complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Miniſters.</note> Monſieur <hi>Vareſi</hi> the Popes <hi>Nuncio, Contarini</hi> the Venetian Embaſſadour, Count <hi>Ferreri</hi> the Savoyan Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, the Abbot <hi>Gondi</hi> Reſident for the Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> Count <hi>Baglioni</hi> Reſident of <hi>Mantua,</hi> and all the other Miniſters of the Potentates and Princes friends to <hi>France</hi> came to congratulate with the Queen and the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi> for the important Conqueſt of the King.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the news that the Count <hi>de Eſtree</hi> Lieutenant General,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Eſtree's</hi> Conqueſt in <hi>America.</hi>
               </note> and Vice Admiral of <hi>France</hi> with the Fleet he commanded in the American Seas had retaken in <hi>December</hi> the Iſle of <hi>Cayenn</hi> from the Hollanders, and had made
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29680:28"/>
the Gariſon priſoners of War. So great and happy ſucceſſes all at once gave no leſs terror to the Confederates, and aſtoniſhment to the moſt puiſſant Neuters, than confidence to the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours to deſign new enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Monſieur commands the Army in <hi>Artois.</hi>
               </note>After the King had given all neceſſary orders concerning his great deſigns, and had put a ſtrong Gariſon into <hi>Valencien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> for the moſt part drawn out of the Regiments of the Suitzers, he decamped on the twenty firſt of <hi>March,</hi> and the ſame day he gave to Monſieur his only Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the command of an Army for <hi>Artois</hi> of four Squadrons and twenty Battalions. His Majeſty choſe to ſerve under his Royal Highneſs the Marſhal <hi>de Humieres:</hi> For Lieutenant Generals, the Prince of <hi>Soubiſe,</hi> and the Count <hi>de Pleſſis:</hi> For Marſhals of the Camp Monſieur
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:29680:28"/>
               <hi>le Mott</hi> who had block'd up St. <hi>Omers,</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Albert,</hi> the Chevalier <hi>de Sourdis,</hi> and <hi>Stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa:</hi> for Brigadiers of the Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Marquis <hi>Gourney,</hi> and of <hi>Bordages:</hi> for Brigadiers of the Infantry, <hi>Aubarede, Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes, Souvroy,</hi> and <hi>Phiffer:</hi> for Major General, Monſieur <hi>de Montmont</hi> Captain of the Guards: for chief Engineer Monſieur <hi>de Choiſy:</hi> for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the Artillery, the Marquis <hi>de Frezeliere:</hi> and for Intendant, Monſieur <hi>Roberto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King kept with himſelf to ſerve him in his Army,<note place="margin">The Troops and Officers about the Kings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> the Marſhals <hi>Scomberg, Luxembourg, Feuillade,</hi> and <hi>Lorges:</hi> for Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Generals, the Duke of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> the Marquis of <hi>Renel, Cardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niere,</hi> the Count <hi>de Avergne</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Villeroy:</hi> For Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Count St. <hi>Geran,</hi> the Marquis and Chevalier <hi>de
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29680:29"/>
Tilladet</hi> Brothers, and the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine <hi>Birkenfield:</hi> For Aides <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Chevalier <hi>Vandôme,</hi> the Princes <hi>d' Harcourt</hi> and <hi>d' Elboeuf,</hi> the Marquis <hi>d' Angeau</hi> and <hi>d' Arcy,</hi> of <hi>Chiverni, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vois,</hi> and the Chevalier <hi>Nogeut:</hi> For Brigadiers of the Cavalry, <hi>Jauvelle la Fitte, Nonan de Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Buzunvil, Roſe,</hi> and <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lart:</hi> for Brigadiers of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry, <hi>Rubentel, Salis, Tracy, de Uxelles, ville Chauve</hi> and <hi>Joſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaux:</hi> for chief Engineer <hi>Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban:</hi> for Intendant of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Monſieur <hi>Bretevil</hi> in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Monſieur St. <hi>Ponaüge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Siege of <hi>Cambray.</hi>
               </note>The King incamp'd that night at <hi>Haſpre,</hi> and on the twenty ſecond he ſate down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Cambray.</hi> He took a turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the place, and would view it within muſquet ſhot. He made them draw the lines of circumvallation and contravalla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:29680:29"/>
Aſſoon as the news of the Siege was ſpread abroad, the Peaſants from all places of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardy</hi> ran thither according to the orders they had received, and they the more willingly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed becauſe they had been for a long time oppreſſ'd by the contributions and continual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodes of that Gariſon. This made them very earneſtly wiſh for the Siege ever ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the War, and it was the end of all their deſires which they expreſſed in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations which they gave the King in his return from the laſt Campain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cambray</hi> is the ſtrongeſt place,<note place="margin">Its fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</note> and the moſt important of all the Netherlands. The <hi>Eſcaut</hi> runs thorow it and fils all its ditches: it is alſo regularly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with Ramparts, Baſtions, Halfmoons, and with two Forts:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29680:30"/>
and commanded by a Citadel of a ſquare form, which is ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from it; and beſides its Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, Halfmoons, and ditches, is placed in a moſt advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſcituation. The place is the more conſiderable for being the capital City of <hi>Cambreſis,</hi> and the Metropolitan Seat of the greateſt part of the low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Catholicks, and for having a Church fil'd with many rich Gifts and of great Revenue and eccleſiaſtical Dignities. They ſay that it was very famous even in the time of the Romans. It got a great reputation under <hi>Clodion</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> when he rendred himſelf maſter of it with the loſs of 50000 men who were ſacrificed at the taking of it as well of the Beſiegers part as of the beſieged: The parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular care which <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth took to fortifie it, very much
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29680:30"/>
augmented its reputation, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it has been ſo well eſtabliſhed in the Wars of our Age, that it hath always paſſed for the moſt formidable place in the whole ſeventeen Provinces. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it was a mortal ſcourge to the ſides of <hi>France,</hi> gave no repoſe to <hi>Picardy,</hi> threatned the <hi>Sein</hi> it ſelf, and in the times of war gather'd ſo great contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it not only ſuppli'd it ſelf but was in a condition to furniſh with neceſſaries all the Catholick places in its neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, and to give ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence to abundance of Troops, ſerving alſo in the mean time for a Refuge to all ſorts of crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals. The King being ſenſibly touch'd with the evils cauſed by this place to ſo great part of his Realm, would by all means give a remedy thereto, and therefore he then ſhut his eyes againſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29680:31"/>
all the aſſaults of the Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts as we have marked, and formed the project of taking of <hi>Cambray,</hi> as well as <hi>Valenciennes</hi> by getting into his hands <hi>Conde</hi> and <hi>Bouchain.</hi> After the taking of thoſe two laſt named places, he never left the Gariſons of the former to be in any quiet, he put a ſtop to their inroads, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred his ſubjects from paying the contributions. He made the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron <hi>de Quincy</hi> to keep the field, to take or ſcatter their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voies, and ſo placed his Troops when the Winter was far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced in quarters that they might be in a readineſs, by the Siege of thoſe places and by taking them in, to put an end to the cauſes of ſo many troubles.</p>
            <p>By this means he eſtabliſh'd the repoſe of his own Realm, put himſelf in a condition of carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:29680:31"/>
the War into his Enemies Country. He diſmember'd one of the moſt conſiderable parts of the Monarchy of <hi>Spain,</hi> and facilitated the progreſs of his Arms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Pedro Savala</hi> a native of <hi>Biſcay</hi> was Governour of the Town and Cittadel.<note place="margin">And Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> He was a man that had ſpent forty years of his Life in the ſervice of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique King, and whoſe Age and experience gotten in the wars made him to be very much eſteemed. The Gariſon was compoſed of about one thouſand horſe and of the Regiments of the Infantry of <hi>Vaudemont, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenbery, Tilly,</hi> one of Hollanders, two Spaniſh of the old Body and one of Walloons.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty made both the City and the Cittadel to be ſhut up within the lines,<note place="margin">The diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Quarters.</note> and cauſed divers Bridges to be layd
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:29680:32"/>
over the <hi>Eſcaut</hi> for communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then he thus ordered the Quarters. He choſe his own at <hi>Avain</hi> on the ſide of the Citadel, and kept with him the Marſhal <hi>Feuillade.</hi> The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal <hi>Lorges</hi> had his on the right ſide of that of the Kings in a place named <hi>Eſcaud'auvers</hi> on the other ſide of the Town and citadel towards the Gate of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenciennes.</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> took his Quarters on the left hand on this ſide St. <hi>Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres</hi> neer to <hi>Chantigneute,</hi> and Marſhal <hi>Schomberg</hi> took up all that part which is on this ſide the <hi>Eſcaut</hi> from new Town to <hi>Cantimpre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Succours hindred.</note>His Majeſty ſent the Baron <hi>de Quincy</hi> with a Body of Horſe on the ſide of <hi>Bavay</hi> in <hi>Hanault</hi> in the neighbourhood of <hi>Mons</hi> as much to oppoſe all ſuccour as to trouble the Commerce
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29680:32"/>
of thoſe places and there to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the enemy.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi> ſeeing <hi>Valenciennes</hi> taken,<note place="margin">Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to relieve <hi>Cambray.</hi>
               </note> and all there de ſigns which they had for to ſuccour it rendered unprofitable, they formed new ones together, to oppoſe the enterpriſes of the King. They did not all doubt but that his Majeſty would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide they determined not to ſuccour <hi>Cambray,</hi> whether it were that they imagined that place, being one of the ſtrongeſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> would of it ſelf render all the Endeavours of the King vain, or that they deſpaired to be able to releive it, being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed about as it was with <hi>Valenciennes, Conde, Bouchaine, Dovay,</hi> and other places of the like Importance. However it was, they rendeſvouz'd their Troops
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29680:33"/>
in the Territory of <hi>Aſneſt</hi> neer to <hi>Gaunt,</hi> and publiſhed that they would oppoſe the deſigns the French might have againſt St. <hi>Omers,</hi> or to revenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the loſs they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by beſieging ſome place of the French upon the River <hi>Lys</hi> or in the French <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The places on the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe menaces of the enemy cauſed the King to write to <hi>Monſieur</hi> his Brother to ſuſpend the ſiege of St. <hi>Omer</hi> till he ſhould receive new orders, and ſent in the mean time Marquis <hi>Lovuis</hi> and the <hi>Gens de Arms</hi> in Walloon <hi>Flanders</hi> and upon the <hi>Lys</hi> to provide for the ſecurity of thoſe places.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The beſieged ſally forth.</note>In the mean time the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or of <hi>Cambray</hi> began on the twenty fourth of <hi>March</hi> to give ſome proofs of that vigorous reſiſtance which he intended to make. He cauſed three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:29680:33"/>
horſe to make a Sally by the Gates of <hi>Selles</hi> and <hi>Cantim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre</hi> upon the Quarters of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal <hi>Schomberg,</hi> ſeparated in many Bands to the end that they might view the beſiegers without being perceived, and alſo give them a means to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance further, if occaſion ſhould offer. They were not come for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward above an hundred and fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty paces, but they were encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd with a ſmall number of Cavaliers under the Conduct of Collonel <hi>Roſe,</hi> who purſued them even to the Paliſſade, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſome and taking others priſoners, where he himſelf was wounded.</p>
            <p>The lines being perfected by the continual labour of the Soldiers and of the Peaſants of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardy,</hi> the King reſolved to open the Trenches on the twenty eighth at night. At that time ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:29680:34"/>
there a great number of Voluntiers,<note place="margin">The arrival of the Prince of <hi>Soiſons.</hi>
               </note> among which were Prince <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Savoy</hi> Count of <hi>Soiſſons;</hi> Prince <hi>Philip</hi> Chevalier of <hi>Savoy,</hi> The Prince of <hi>Mourges &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Trenches Opened.</note>They reſolv'd to make the Attacque on the Quarters of Marſhal <hi>Lorges,</hi> againſt two Half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moons, one of which covered the Gate of <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> and the other was on the left ſide of the ſame Gate.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marſhal</hi> Schom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergs <hi>Guards.</hi>
               </note> His Majeſty cauſed the firſt Guard to be mounted in his preſence by Marſhal <hi>Schomberg,</hi> the Marquis <hi>Reſnel</hi> Leiutenant General, the Count St. <hi>Geran</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Prince <hi>de Harcourt</hi> Ayde <hi>de Camp,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Rubentel</hi> Briga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of the Infantry, with three Battalions of the French Guards and ſix Squadrons under <hi>Jau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velle</hi> Brigadier of the Cavalry, followed by one of the Guards
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29680:34"/>
of the Body of <hi>Noailles,</hi> one of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> one of the white Muſqueteers, one of the <hi>Croates,</hi> one of the <hi>Dauphins</hi> Regiment, and one of <hi>Orleans.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The King comes into the Trench.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The King getting away from his Train would needs ſee the beginning of the works accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied only with the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier <hi>Vandôme</hi> and the Prince <hi>d' Harcourt.</hi> The beſieged fired ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly; but they kill'd but four ſoldiers which were cut off with one ſhot of a Cannon the next day in the morning.<note place="margin">M. Fivilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des <hi>Guard;</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The twenty ninth at night the Guard was releived by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal <hi>Feuillade: Cardonniere</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General, Marquis <hi>Tilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> Marquis Chiverny Ayde <hi>de Camp, Salis</hi> Brigadier of the Infantry, with two Battalions of the Guards of <hi>Swiſſes</hi> and one of <hi>Salis</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by Monſieur <hi>Le Fitte</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:29680:35"/>
Brigadier of the Cavalry, with two Squadrons of the Guard of the Body of <hi>Duras</hi> and <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and four others of the black Muſqueteers, of the <hi>Dauphins, Orleans,</hi> and <hi>Croates.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Battery raiſed.</note> The morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and all the day following a Battery which they had raiſed on the River on the ſide of Newtown, and which had let them ſee plainly the fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they were to attaque, began very much to incommode the Beſieged. From the thirtieth of <hi>March</hi> at night, to the firſt of <hi>April</hi> the Trench was carried within an hundred and fifty paces of the Counterſcarp with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any loſs.<note place="margin">M. Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgs <hi>Guard.</hi>
               </note> Marſhal <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> was there that day, and with him the Count <hi>Auvergne</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General, Chevalier <hi>Tilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> Marquis <hi>de Cavois</hi> Aide <hi>de Camp, Tracy</hi> Brigadier of the Infantry, with
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:29680:35"/>
three Battalions, two of the French Guards and one of <hi>Salis,</hi> and ſix Squadrons under <hi>Auger</hi> Brigadier of the Cavalry, two of which Squadrons were of the Guards <hi>de Corps</hi> of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ailles</hi> and <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> one of the Muſqueteers, one of St. <hi>Aig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan,</hi> one of <hi>Heaudicourt,</hi> and one of <hi>Bligny.</hi> In the mean time the beſieged performed very well their parts. They cauſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very night great fires to be made upon the plain of the Counterſcarp, to diſcover and overthrow the enemies works.</p>
            <p>They every day fallied forth,<note place="margin">A Sally of the Beſieged.</note> which they would have ſtill continued without doubt, but that the Rains made the earth ſo ſlippery that hindred the Guard in the Trenches from working, ſo that they had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do. However they loſt five priſoners and one Engineer,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:29680:36"/>
who being diſcontented with the Spaniards came and render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf in the Camp.</p>
            <p>The 2 of <hi>April</hi> the Trench being finiſhed the King was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to attacque the two half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moons.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M. Fuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade</hi> his Guard: The halfmoons attacqu'd.</note> It was the Marſhal <hi>Feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>illades</hi> day, with the Count <hi>de Auvergny</hi> Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the Marquis <hi>Tilladet</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Prince <hi>de El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boeuf</hi> Aide <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>de Uxelles</hi> Brigadier of the Infantry at the head of four Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talions of the Royal Regiments and of the <hi>Dauphins,</hi> ſuſteined by the Marquis of <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enval</hi> Brigadier of the Cavalry, with a Squadron of the Life Guards, and five Squadrons of Light Horſe. Theſe Troops not only carried the two halfmoons but they alſo ſiezed an angle of an Horn work on the ſide of the Fort of <hi>Selles.</hi> The Beſieged de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:29680:36"/>
themſelves very manful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the taking of thoſe poſts coſt the French an hundred ſoldiers and as many wounded.</p>
            <p>The Commander and Officers of the Town ſeeing on the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeth that the mines were fixed to the Body of the place,<note place="margin">The Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</note> and fearing the like inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of that of <hi>Conde,</hi> and that ſo lately of <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving they ſhould not ſtay the ſpringing the Mine, nor that they ſhould be able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the aſſault, they ſent out a party late at night, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to capitulate. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour thought it was pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to conſerve for his Prince a Gariſon compoſed of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good Troops, and he alſo flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd himſelf with the hope that he might be able to keep the Cittadel for a long time, and make them to draw out the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:29680:37"/>
Siege ſo long that it might give time to the Confederates to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour them, and to put ſome ſtop that way to the Torrent of the Deſignes and Conqueſts of the King, or at leaſt to deſtroy or conſiderably to infeeble his Army. Aſſoon as the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation was demanded,<note place="margin">A Truce.</note> his Majeſty agreed to a Truce for twenty four hours, and the Count <hi>de Auvergne</hi> receiv'd the hoſtages.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgs <hi>Guard.</hi>
               </note>The Guard was releiv'd that night from the third to the fourth by Marſhal <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> the Duke <hi>de Villeroy</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General, Chevalier <hi>Tilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> Chevalier <hi>Vandôme</hi> Aide <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Counts of <hi>Tallard</hi> and <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanver</hi> the one Brigadier of the Cavalry, and the other of the Infantry, with four Battalions, half of <hi>Alſace</hi> and half on <hi>Fuzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers,</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:29680:37"/>
and ſix Squadrons, one of the Guards <hi>de Corps</hi> and five of Light Horſe.</p>
            <p>The fourth the Marſhal <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburg</hi> was advertiz'd that Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Ris</hi> Commander of the Cavalry in <hi>Cambray,</hi> and Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur <hi>Couaruvias</hi> Maſter <hi>de Camp</hi> of a Spaniſh <hi>Tirce,</hi> demanded to ſpeak with the King. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>de Angeau</hi> introduced them into the Kings Tent, who gave them Orders for the retreat of the Gariſon into the Citadel. They firſt of all abandoned one Gate of the Town, then the Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts and the Streets, and left <hi>Cambray</hi> in the power of the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was on the fifth that this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was executed,<note place="margin">They poſſeſs the Town.</note> which paſſed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry peacebly. Two Battalions of the French Guards, one of the Guards of Swiſſes, one of <hi>Salis,</hi> and a Squadron of the Guards of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:29680:38"/>
Body poſſeſſed themſelves of all the Poſts aſſoon as the Gariſon were gone to ſecure themſelves in the Cittadel. Then the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtages on either ſide were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred and the Truce ceaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty grants the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges to the Town.</note>The Clergy and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of the Town came to render their Homage to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, who ſigned to the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation and granted to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants the ſame priviledges which he had granted to thoſe of <hi>Liſle</hi> on the like occaſion, and to the Clergy the ſame Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes which thoſe of <hi>Tournay</hi> had obtained in 1667, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Archbiſhop to reſide at <hi>Cambray,</hi> provided that he would take an oath of fidelity, which he did.<note place="margin">He is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemented by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The Count <hi>Ferreri</hi> Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who that day ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the Camp to reſide neer his Majeſty, teſtified to him in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:29680:38"/>
the name of their Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes the part which they took in his happy ſucceſſes, and he was received with all the marks of a particular eſteem.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal <hi>d' Eſtree</hi> came thither alſo and was lodged with the Cardinal of <hi>Bouillon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And by the Cardinal <hi>de Eſtree.</hi>
               </note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rendred his Devoir to his Majeſty: and after a few days that he had reſided there he was nominated to go to <hi>Rome</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his Brother Embaſſadour there.</p>
            <p>Monſieur being arrived on the twenty fourth of <hi>March</hi> in the Camp of his Army at <hi>Blandeck,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Siege of St. <hi>Omers.</hi>
               </note> and having made every thing ready, he diſpoſed himſelf for the Siege of St. <hi>Omer.</hi> It is one of the principal places of <hi>Artots</hi> and of the Spaniſh <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands;</hi> conſiderable for its ſituation, for its fortifications, for the inconvenience it gave to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:29680:39"/>
               <hi>France,</hi> and for the contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it raiſed from thence. It trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Commerce of <hi>Calais,</hi> and divided the conquered Countries betwixt <hi>Arraes</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> and deſolated all <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonnois.</hi> The King had the year paſt propoſed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to deliver theſe Countries from all thoſe evils which this place cauſed.<note place="margin">The King diſpoſes things for the Siege.</note> To which effect he took the occaſion of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage from the Siege of <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> where the Army of the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates were engaged, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ordered Marquis <hi>Louvis</hi> to aſſiſt at the Siege of <hi>Aire,</hi> which Marſhal <hi>de Humieres</hi> had enterpriſed, and which place was carried in few daies, his Majeſty cover'd his deſigns which he had againſt St. <hi>Omers</hi> in taking of that, publiſhing that he did it to be revenged for the Siege of <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> and it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:29680:39"/>
was under the ſame pretence that at the ſame time he cauſed <hi>Linch</hi> to be taken by the ſame Marſhal. Having at laſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Siege of <hi>Maſtricht</hi> to be raiſed by Marſhal <hi>Schomberg,</hi> his Majeſty order'd the Marſhal <hi>de Humieres</hi> as Governour of the Countries conquer'd in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> to make himſelf maſter of all the Poſts that encompaſſed St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and to take from it all manner of communication by ſending certain Troops into the field. All this was punctually executed. The Marſhal cauſed the Caſtle of <hi>Caſſel</hi> to be forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſent in the month of <hi>March,</hi> the laſt year Monſieur <hi>de Mommont</hi> Captain of the Guards, and Brigadier of the Infantry, to ſieſe on <hi>Nieulet, Bac, Momelin, Clair-Marais,</hi> and other parts round about. It was in this Action that Count
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:29680:40"/>
               <hi>Genlis</hi> was kill'd in forcing a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubt at the head of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Crown, of which he was Collonel. Having at laſt left the command of his Troops to <hi>la Motte</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> he came to the Kings Camp, where he let his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs underſtand under whom he commanded, the condition in which he had left all things.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of <hi>St. Omers.</hi>
               </note>St. <hi>Omer</hi> is the chief City of the Spaniſh <hi>Artois,</hi> ſituate on the River <hi>Aae,</hi> fortified with walls, Baſtions, Halfmoons, Ditches, Marſhes, and Lakes, where there are little floting Iſlands. They believe by tradition in this Country that this is the famous Road of <hi>Iccius,</hi> where <hi>Caeſar</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked his men when he went to war upon the Britains, and they would have the ſand and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel which is found thereabouts to be an aſſured mark that the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:29680:40"/>
Sea did heretofore flow ſo far as it. The place was firſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sithien,</hi> it chang'd its name, and from a ſimple Caſtle as it was became a City in the time of St. <hi>Omer</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Terroü<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane.</hi> The people that inhabit it, the riches in which they abound, the Canal for commerce named the New-Foſs, and the Abby of St. <hi>Bertin,</hi> render it as cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brous as its Arms, and its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>It had within the place a Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of 2000 foot and 500 Horſe:<note place="margin">The Gariſon.</note> beſides the <hi>Militia</hi> and the Burgueſſes. St. <hi>Vegnant</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded there. But the Prince of <hi>Robeck</hi> as Governour of the Spaniſh <hi>Artois</hi> had there the chief place.</p>
            <p>Monſieur having viſited the Poſts and inveſted the place,<note place="margin">The quarters taken up by Monſieur.</note> he diſtributed the Quarters. He took his own called the Generals
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:29680:41"/>
Quarter at <hi>Blandeck,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with him the Marſhal <hi>de Humieres,</hi> Count <hi>dis Pleſſis</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General, <hi>Stouppe</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> with two Battalions of <hi>Navarre,</hi> one of <hi>Humieres,</hi> and two of <hi>Phiffer;</hi> and two Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of St. <hi>Germain Bauprie,</hi> and one of <hi>Vaines.</hi> He poſted the Price of <hi>Soubiſe</hi> Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral in the way to <hi>Arques</hi> with Monſieur <hi>de Alber</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp, de Auberade</hi> Brigadier, with two Battalions of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and two of <hi>Vaiſſeans.</hi> At <hi>Clairmarais</hi> one Battalion of <hi>Conty</hi> under Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Lare</hi> Maſter <hi>de Camp.</hi> At old Caſtle upon the old Canal, ſix Companies of the <hi>Dauphins</hi> Dragoons. At <hi>Nieulet la Motte</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> with two of <hi>Greeders</hi> Battalions, and one of <hi>Phiffer,</hi> ſix Companies of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons of the Collonel Generals, and one Squadron of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:29680:41"/>
of <hi>de Aumounts.</hi> At the Fort of <hi>Bac</hi> a Battalion of <hi>Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> at St. <hi>Momelin</hi> a Battalion of the Crown under the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier <hi>de Genlis,</hi> the King having gratified him with his Brothers Regiment: At <hi>Tilque</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>de Trouſſe</hi> Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, the Chevalier <hi>Sour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>Bordages</hi> Brigadier with a Battalion of the Royal Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Rouſſillon,</hi> and two of Italians. At <hi>Ovatte</hi> one Battali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Crown. At <hi>Tattinghen Frezelier</hi> Lieutenant General of of the Artillery with the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Tourain</hi> which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and <hi>Bordages</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Horſe. At <hi>Viſque</hi> ſix Companies of Dragoons of the <hi>Dauphins</hi> under Monſieur <hi>de Longueval.</hi> At <hi>Viſerne</hi> two Squadrons of <hi>Gournay,</hi> who as Brigadier of the Cavalry com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:29680:42"/>
all thoſe who ſerved at the Siege.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Siege not preſſed.</note>Thus without drawing the Lines St. <hi>Omer</hi> was inveſted, and Monſieur would preſently have fallen to attaque it, but that his Army being yet weak and the great circuit of the place, and the Marſhes, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a far greater number of men, ſo that he was fain to ſtay for the coming of other Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions and the orders the King would give; beſides, the Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery was not yet come into the Camp being hindred by the rains, till juſt then. However in the mean time they carried the Redout of <hi>Colear</hi> and ſome other Poſts, and endeavoured to aſſure the communication of their Quarters to hinder all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Recruits. ſent to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur.</note>On the twenty eighth of <hi>March</hi> the Duke <hi>de Aumont</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:29680:42"/>
of <hi>Bullonois</hi> ſent him a great convoy, and after a little time came himſelf into the Camp of his Royal Highneſs with all ſorts of munitions and with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 2000 Foot and 500 Horſe of the <hi>Militia</hi> of War within his goverment. Monſieur en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced the quarters of <hi>Clairma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rais</hi> and <hi>Nieurlet</hi> with the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and that of <hi>Tilque</hi> with the Cavalrie.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſuccours being come,<note place="margin">Attaque of the Fort <hi>Vaches.</hi>
               </note> and the arrival of the Artillery made Monſieur take a reſolution to aſſault the Fort <hi>Vaches,</hi> or the Cow, which ſecured the moſt feeble places of the Town. This Fort is on the ſide of the Gate of the high Bridge, which was defended with 400 Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loons. On the twenty ninth they raiſed a Battery of four pieces of Canon to batter a ruin, and to make a lodgment to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:29680:43"/>
them there. At night the ſame day the beſieged made a very vigorous ſally with a deſign to nail up the Canon and ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow their Lodgment.<note place="margin">The beſieged ſally.</note> Monſieur <hi>de Albert</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp</hi> with 400 of the Regiment of <hi>Navarre</hi> conducted by his Lieutenant Collonel, the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>Souvray,</hi> after a very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate diſpute forced the beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to reenter the place, purſuing them even to the Counterſcarp, <hi>d' Albret</hi> had one horſe killed under him in this Action and loſt about twenty men. The Beſieged loſt double the number both killed and wounded, the moſt conſiderable priſoners were an Ayd Major and another Officer of a Walloon Regiment, who were taken priſoners with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in twenty paces of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſcarp.</p>
            <p>At that time Monſieur recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:29680:43"/>
ten Battalions and ſome Squadrons which the King ſent him,<note place="margin">Recruits ſent from the King.</note> and the ſecond of <hi>April</hi> the King ſent to them to open the Trenches. His Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs deſigned two Attaques, one at <hi>Tattinghen</hi> againſt a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of an horn Work the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt place of all the Works, and the other on the Fort <hi>Vaches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the fourth to the fifth at night Monſieur made the Guard be mounted for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the Trench by the Count <hi>du Pleſſis</hi> Lieutenant General,<note place="margin">The Trenches opened. Guard of <hi>du Pleſſis.</hi>
               </note> Monſieur <hi>la Mette</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> Monſieur <hi>d' Aubarede</hi> Brigadier of the Infantry with two Battalions of <hi>Navarre</hi> who were placed on the right ſide of the Trench, and two of <hi>Freze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> or <hi>Tourain</hi> and <hi>Phiffer</hi> on the left ſide back'd by four Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of <hi>Gournay</hi> and <hi>Vaines,</hi> and at the ſame time the Trench
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:29680:44"/>
was alſo opened at the Fort <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collonel <hi>Vaine</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note> The Beſieged did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive theſe attaques till the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when they failed not to ply us with their Canon, and to ſhoot into our Camp, where Collonel <hi>Vaine</hi> was killed doing his duty at the head of his Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Marquis <hi>la Trouſſe</hi> hes Guard.</note>From the fifth to the ſixth at night the Guard was relieved by the Marquis <hi>la Trouſſe</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General, <hi>Stoup</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp,</hi> with the Regiments of <hi>Anjou</hi> and of the Italian <hi>Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotti. Frezelier</hi> had that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning made ready ten pieces of Canon at the quarter of <hi>Tatting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hen</hi> which played with very good ſucceſs, and he diſpoſed another Battery of four pieces againſt the Cow-Fort.</p>
            <p>From the ſixth to the ſeventh was the day of Prince <hi>de Soubiſe</hi> Lieutenant General,<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſes</hi> Guard.</note> with the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:29680:44"/>
Chevalier <hi>de Sourdis</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp</hi> at the head of four Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions,<note place="margin">The Fort ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> two of the Queens Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and two of <hi>Vaiſſeaux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the ſeventh to the eight night Monſieur <hi>de Albert</hi> was on the Guard of the Trench till the Attaque of <hi>Tattinghen.</hi> On the other ſide Count <hi>du Pleſſis</hi> with the Battalions of <hi>Navarre</hi> and <hi>Anjou</hi> and the Italian, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by the <hi>Dauphins</hi> Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons inveſted the Cowfort on the ſide of the water Gate. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur thought good to attempt that attaque, for that the fort was already in an ill Condition by the Canon, and incommod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a certain Lodgment which they had made there. The Beſieged who beleiv'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves yet in a Condition to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it, imagined that it was but a falſe Attacque. But the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons commanded by Monſieur
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:29680:45"/>
               <hi>Longevall</hi> and by the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier <hi>Quevilly</hi> his Lieutenant, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, and with their Swords in their hands kill'd all that reſiſted, and making priſoners ſome of the Enemy, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Quarter. Collonel <hi>Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> with one of their beſt Officers were kill'd upon the place, and <hi>Quevilly</hi> fighting was there wounded. In the mean time Count <hi>du Pleſſis</hi> with thoſe Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talions which we nominated aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted the ſide of the high Bridge: but the Cannons which were placed there oppoſed his paſſage. Without this Obſtacle he had put a terror into the Town by taking from them all hopes of Releif by <hi>Nieurlet</hi> and <hi>Bac,</hi> and had reduced them to the ſame Extremity as they were in at <hi>Valenciennes</hi> in the attaque of the Crown work.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:29680:45"/>The Chiefs and the Generals of the low Countrys did not looſe a moment in reſiſting the torrent of the Conqueſt of <hi>France.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates.</note> The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> having aſſembled his Infantry and Cavalry of the Hollanders in the Dutch <hi>Flanders</hi> he re-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd them with the Regiments of <hi>Holſtein, de Orsbeck</hi> and other Hollanders which ſerv'd in <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves,</hi> and with an Army of about 12000 horſe and of forty Battali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the leaſt of which contained 800 men, he came to <hi>Anvers</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Villa Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſa</hi> to conſult with him the means of ſaving thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces from being wholly over-run, and to put the Flemings out of that Conſternation they were in by ſome conſiderable Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>The King, who was not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that the forces of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:29680:46"/>
were much greater than thoſe of his Army,<note place="margin">The King ſends Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours to Monſieur.</note> which he had given to Monſieur, and that they might eaſily be able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ſome Siege or elſe to cauſe Monſieur to raiſe his Siege about St. <hi>Omer:</hi> to prevent all their enterpriſes he cauſed <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donniere</hi> Commiſſary General of the Cavalry and Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, to leave his Camp with twenty ſix Squadrons with deſign to refreſh themſelves for ſome days in new Quarters, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſending preſently after them Marſhall <hi>Luxemburg</hi> with two Companies of Muſqueteers and nine Batalions under <hi>Tracy,</hi> and gave the Marſhal order to joyn all thoſe Troops together with the <hi>Gens d' Arms</hi> which had already paſt to <hi>Liſle</hi> and other reinforcements, to make head againſt the enemy, and to cover Monſieurs Siege, and to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:29680:46"/>
give time to Marquis <hi>Louvis</hi> to provide for the ſurety of the places on the Frontiers, as <hi>Liſle, Courtray</hi> and others, in all which he ſo diſpoſed things that they might be able to make a long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in caſe they were attaqu'd.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide Monſieur ſent alſo for precaution one Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion to <hi>Bergue,</hi> and another to <hi>Dunkirk</hi> to put thoſe two mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time places in a condition to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves.</p>
            <p>All theſe precautions of the French did very much thwart the Council that was held at <hi>Anvers.</hi> The Confederates con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that the King being maſter of <hi>Cambray,</hi> which Siege was very much advanced and Monſieur of S. <hi>Omer,</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty might then reunite all his forces, and force them to a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel or raiſe their Siege if they ſhould undertake any, aſſoon as
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:29680:47"/>
they ſhould be arrived in the ſame Province under <hi>Oudenard,</hi> although they were much more ſtrong, by reaſon that the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts had joyned them.<note place="margin">The deliber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates againſt theirs own maxims.</note> Thus the Council could not but agree to the advice of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who would preſently oppoſe them in their Enterpriſe againſt St. <hi>Omer,</hi> flattering themſelves to have found an occaſion of revenging themſelves for being forced to raiſe their Siege at <hi>Maiſtricht</hi> by the French, of which Town they had made themſelves ſure. And ſince Sieges had not been ſo proſperous to them, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved now to try the Fortune of a Battel, in which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to themſelves better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Why they conſented to a Battel.</note>The Spaniards, contrary to their ordinary Reſolutions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hazarding a Battel, were
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:29680:47"/>
at this time perſwaded that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ſhould give Battel if he found a favourabla oportunity. For he thereby ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded nothing of theirs if he did it, neither the Reputation of their Arms nor the loſs of their Troops; and they might by this means of a Battel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their own eſtates at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others charge, or put a ſtop to an entire overthrow. The Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers alſo did not oppoſe it, ſuppoſing that in caſe of ill Fortune, they ought always to defend the Catholique Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, againſt which they very well ſaw the King muſt carry his Arms, before he could come to them.</p>
            <p>But not to forget too long what paſſed before <hi>Cambray, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vella</hi> who had retired out of the Citty with the Gariſon into the Citadel cauſed part of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:29680:48"/>
horſe to be lodg'd in the Ditches, the place not being able to contain them all, and he cauſed all thoſe as were uſeleſs to be killed, and ſo diſpoſed himſelf and Gariſon for a vigorous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. He found himſelf alſo very well provided of all ſorts of ammunition as well as of ſoldiers, and in a place that both Nature and Art had rendred very formidable to the Vulgar, ſo that they believed this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs would be the Chruch yard of all the French that ſhould endeavour to take it. And <hi>Ris</hi> who commanded the Cavalry told the Marquis <hi>de Angeau</hi> with much confidence when he preſented him to his Majeſty to capitulate about the Town, that the Cittadel would coſt the King that Summers work How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he durſt not accept the Challenge the Marquis made
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:29680:48"/>
him that he would lay with him ten thouſand Crowns, that it would not hold out to the middle of the Spring, which was already far advanced.<note place="margin">The Truce ceaſes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>On the fifth of <hi>April</hi> the Hoſtages were rendred and the Truce ended, and the King cauſed the Town on that ſide towards the Cittadel to be bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricaded, and thoſe ſtreets that adjoyned neer it,<note place="margin">Batteries raiſed.</note> and raiſed two Batteries one on the rampart of the Town and the other in the Camp at the Quarter of the Marſhal <hi>Lorges.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Attaque diſpoſed.</note> Theſe two Batteries were ſeconded by two attacques which they made, the one by the plain, the other on the ſide of the Gate of <hi>Valenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enes</hi> againſt two Baſtions and two halfmoons of the Citadel which look'd on that ſide of the City.<note place="margin">The Trench opened.</note> The ſame night they opened the Trench after the ſame manner
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:29680:49"/>
as they formerly did, with this only difference that the King would not permit but one Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Officer to each Guard. The Army being now not ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous by reaſon of the detach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which he had ſent to ſtrengthen Monſieur,<note place="margin">The King ſpares his Soldiers.</note> and the place beſieged look'd on as a murtherer, the King took all the ways he could to ſpare his Soldiers, and therefore would not preſs the enterpriſe, being more deſirous to ſacrifice Time in the Siege than his Troops. the firſt night the Beſieged wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed great vigour and briskneſs, killing or wounding with their Artillery above twenty five Soldiers in the Guard in the Trench.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">M. <hi>Louvis</hi> returns to the Camp.</note>On the ſixth the Marquis <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis</hi> returned to the Camp from viſiting the conquered places, after he had put all things in
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:29680:49"/>
ſuch a condition that they need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to fear any ſurpriſe from the Confederates.<note place="margin">And the Duke of <hi>Villeroy.</hi>
               </note> The Duke of <hi>Villeroy</hi> under Marſhal <hi>Scom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> poſſeſſed the Quarter of Marſhal <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> who was gon to favour the enterpriſe of Monſieur as had been ſaid. That night the Beſieged made two ſallies to overthrow the Works,<note place="margin">Two ſallies,</note> but were ſtill beaten back, and they could not hinder them from carrying on the Trench even to the ſide of the Counterſcarp.</p>
            <p>On the ſeventh in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Count <hi>d' Avergne</hi> was wounded with the blow of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non on the head.<note place="margin">Count <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vergne</hi> wounded.</note> 
               <hi>Vigny</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Bombardiers having made ready many mortars, flung the night following an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of Bombs and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſſes into the Cittadel,<note place="margin">The effect of his Bombs.</note> which as if it had been thunder-ſtrook beat down all the top of it, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:29680:50"/>
falling into a Magazin of Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos conſumed it. Thoſe of the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadel endeavoured to anſwer them in the ſame manner in flinging great quantity into the Town and into the Camp, but whether the matter was not good, or that they were ill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, they had no great effect. On the eight the Bombs and Mortars continued to batter the Cittadel and ruined the other Magazins, beat down their <hi>Corps du Guard,</hi> which was to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Gate of the Cittadel, and forced the Beſieged to retire into their caſements or loop-holes: and on the ninth they finiſhed the communication of their Works.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An other Battery.</note>On the tenth there was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Battery raiſed upon the Ramparts on the left ſide of the Town,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> de Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>ſlain.</hi>
               </note> where it began to draw towards the Cittadel. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:29680:50"/>
               <hi>de Reynel</hi> Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Camp-maſter General of the light Horſe, a man of an illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Birth and of great repute for his good ſervice, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly eſteemed for his experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in warlike Affairs, was killed with a Canon ſhot as he was diſcourſing with the Duke de <hi>Villeroy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the eleventh the lines of communication and the courts of Guards being finiſhed, they prepared themſelves for an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taque on a Halfmoon, which cover'd the Baſtion oppoſite to the corner of the Town towards the Gate of <hi>Valenciennes.</hi> The beſieged prevented the attaque by a brisk and vigorous ſally both of Foot and Horſe,<note place="margin">A ſally.</note> but were repulſed by the Marquis <hi>Tilladet</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp</hi> and <hi>d' Uxelles</hi> Brigadier, who were on the Guard in the Trench. The
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:29680:51"/>
Marquis of <hi>Harcourt-Beuvron</hi> at the very ſame time by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the King and the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Officer who commanded,<note place="margin">The Half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moon taken.</note> fell upon the Halfmoon of <hi>Picardy</hi> and carried it: <hi>Champereux</hi> and <hi>Courtine</hi> with a good many Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of that Regiment lodged themſelves in the neck of the Halfmoon. The Ground was very well diſputed and the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged loſt then above 100 men kill'd and wounded.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarp taken.</note>On the eleventh at night to the twelfth the Marſhal <hi>Scom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> relieved the Guard. He attaqued the Counterſcarp by the Kings order with the Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of the Guards and theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Regiments, and lodged themſelves there. The Fight was obſtinate and coſt a great many Officers and Soldiers lives on either ſide: the French loſt among others ſix Officers of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:29680:51"/>
the Guards. <hi>Rouvray</hi> Baron of <hi>Arcancy, Arnoue,</hi> the Chevalier <hi>Courtenay, Sautor, Reger,</hi> and <hi>Parfate;</hi> the Chevalier <hi>Boin</hi> and <hi>Conſtantin</hi> were wounded.</p>
            <p>The day after they began to pierce the Baſtion with their Canon on the left ſide of the Town,<note place="margin">Another Battery.</note> that they might be able to approch with their mine. They alſo raiſed another Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ruine the flanks and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponniers. They alſo made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other lodgment and certain places for their Arms, that they might put their miners under covert.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the King was in great pain for to know the ſucceſs of the enterpriſe at St. <hi>Omers;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The news of the battel of <hi>Caſſel</hi> brought to the Camp.</note> from whence he received news by the Couriers every hour, who had brought him word that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> at the head of the moſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:29680:52"/>
flouriſhing Army that ever yet the States General were maſters of, approached Monſieur with great diligence, but that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Marquis <hi>d' Effiat,</hi> the firſt Eſquire to his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whom he had expreſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched to the King, brought him the news of the Victory which they had had over the Hollanders.</p>
            <p>Monſieur having rendred himſelf maſter of the Cowfort, the ſeventh as we have already mentioned knew by thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which he had detached from his Camp, to obſerve the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> that the Prince had quit <hi>Ypres</hi> with his whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and that he was come to <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hen.</hi> He reſolved to go and encounter him with his Troops, and though he ſeemed to be leſs ſtrong, he would not however looſe the ground he
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:29680:52"/>
had gain'd in that place. He left then to guard the Cowfort and to continue the Attaques on that ſide,<note place="margin">Monſieur leaves the Lines.</note> the Marquis <hi>la Trouſſe</hi> Lieutenant General, and <hi>Stoup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp</hi> with one Battalion of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> one of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> and one of the <hi>Sea-Royal,</hi> one of <hi>Rouſſillon,</hi> and ſome Squadrons of <hi>Bordages</hi> and the Cavalry of <hi>Boulonnois.</hi> He ſent to <hi>Bac, Nieurlet</hi> and <hi>Ouattes,</hi> one Battalion of <hi>Phiffers,</hi> and one of <hi>Greeders</hi> Dragoons, and the reſt of the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonnois.</hi> And ſo being aſſured of divers Poſts about the place, he left the Lines on the ninth in the morning. He preſently ſent away to <hi>Bergue</hi> to adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> to joyn him,<note place="margin">He meets the recruits.</note> and within half a quarter of a league from the Camp upon an Eminence neer <hi>Arque</hi> he found <hi>Cardonniere</hi> with
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:29680:53"/>
twenty ſix Squadrons and with him Monſieur St. <hi>Poüange.</hi> He continued his march to an high place which is between <hi>Caſſel</hi> and the Abby of <hi>Ovattine,</hi> where he encamped. On the tenth in the morning his Army was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enforced by the Marquis of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourn</hi> with the <hi>Gens d' Armery, Revel</hi> with his Brigade of Horſe, and at night by <hi>Tracy</hi> with nine Battalions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ranges his Army in <hi>Battalia.</hi>
               </note>Monſieur found himſelf now at the head of 25000 Comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants 16000 Foot and 9000 Horſe. He began to view his Camp and his Poſts, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood with what diligence the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> came towards him, he put his Army in <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia</hi> on this ſide of a little River called the <hi>Pene.</hi> He gave the command of the right wing which he had placed between <hi>Caſſel</hi> and <hi>Ovattine</hi> in the field
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:29680:53"/>
of <hi>Ablinghen</hi> to the Marſhal <hi>de Humieres,</hi> and placed neer him for Lieutenant General <hi>Cardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier</hi> and the Chevalier <hi>Sourdis</hi> for Marſhal <hi>de Camp.</hi> He gave the left wing which had its ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on this ſide the <hi>Buſcure</hi> to Marſhal <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> who had for his Lieutenant General the Count <hi>du Pleſſis,</hi> and for Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal <hi>de Camp</hi> Monſieur <hi>d' Albret,</hi> and the ſecond line of the left wing he gave to the Prince of <hi>Soubiſe</hi> with order to make uſe of the opportunities that ſhould offer themſelves in the Battel. But you may ſee the order of the Battel drawn in a ſcheme better than in a long diſcourſe, which ſhall be annexed to this.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived advice from the Prince of <hi>Robek,</hi> that aſſured him that Monſieur had not with him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 14000 men, and that he
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:29680:54"/>
had not made any Lines of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvallation and Contravallati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that if his Highneſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the time longer to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour St. <hi>Omers,</hi> it would be too late, becauſe there would come from the Kings Camp great ſtore of Troops to enforce that of Monſieurs. All theſe reaſons obliged the Prince to part from <hi>Ypres</hi> with his Army which conſiſted of 30000 fighting men,<note place="margin">The Armies face one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</note> and encamped that night being the ninth at <hi>Marie-Capel.</hi> He there underſtood that the French were not above a league from him, he put his Army in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Battalia,</hi> and on the tenth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout noon his Army faced that of Monſieurs in five diviſions, it was drawn up on the left ſide of <hi>Caſſel</hi> and on this ſide of the River of <hi>Pene.</hi> He then cauſed his right wing to make an hault neer to <hi>Moulins</hi> a poſt contigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:29680:54"/>
to the village of <hi>Pene,</hi> and his left wing towards the village of <hi>Bauvincourt.</hi> It would be difficult to deſcribe the fair ſhow that this Army made,<note place="margin">The Princes Troops and chief Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note> it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it was compoſed of above 12000 Horſe and 20000 Foot, beſides an other groſs Body of 5 or 6000 horſe which attended continually under the leading of the Count of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> the States General of the Cavalry. The other chief Officers under his Highneſs were Count <hi>Waldeck</hi> Camp Marſhal General, Count <hi>Horn</hi> General of the Artillery: <hi>Vanweblen</hi> Major General, and <hi>Mountpovillan</hi> Serjeant Major.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing that the Prince would undertake,<note place="margin">Their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe.</note> was to relieve St. <hi>Omer</hi> on the ſide of <hi>Back,</hi> which ſeem'd to be the only way left to do it. For this end he commanded his Dragoons to ſieze on the Abby of <hi>Pene,</hi> by
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:29680:55"/>
which action he would cover his march which he intended to take on the right hand.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Oppoſed by Marſhal <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi>
               </note>Monſieur who perceived the Enemy to ſtretch himſelf forth towards the right ſide, ordered Marſhal <hi>Luxemburg</hi> to poſt his Dragoons at <hi>Sainſandoux,</hi> and the Cavalry of the ſecond Line at <hi>Moulin, Balamberg</hi> to cut off their way to <hi>Ovattes</hi> in caſe they ſhould advance on that ſide, and then underſtanding that the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> Dragoons had ſiezed on the Abby of <hi>Pene,</hi> he ſent the Dragoons of <hi>Liſtenoy</hi> and the Regiment of <hi>Lyonnois</hi> to chaſe them thence: but the Prince having reinforced them with ſome Foot, there began in that place a skirmiſh which laſted till night,<note place="margin">A skirmiſh.</note> till the Marſhal <hi>Luxemburg</hi> forced them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and remained maſter of that Poſt, leaving there Soldiers with
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:29680:55"/>
Serjeant for to guard it. Monſieur would have at the ſame time made a general Attaque,<note place="margin">Monſieur could not execute his deſign.</note> but the advantage of the ground which the Enemies poſſeſſed, the paſſage of two Rivers and the day being almoſt ſpent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged hin to defer it.</p>
            <p>On the eleventh in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> very well perceived that he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to give Battel. The day before he found all the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages whereby he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve St. <hi>Omers</hi> faſt ſhut up, and he thought that he was more ſtrong than the Monſieur, for he was yet ignorant of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruits that were come to his Royal Highneſſes Army; and if he had known it, 'twould have been a ſhame for him and for the States General to have left his Poſt.<note place="margin">The Prince reſolves to give battel.</note> He then reſolved to take the occaſion to engage, he
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:29680:56"/>
paſſed the firſt River, and made his Artillery advance; and made the a new aſſault on the Abby of <hi>Pene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paſſes the River.</note> and lodging there a part of his Dragoons, he poſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſome thick ſhrubs neer to <hi>Moulin</hi> ſome Squadrons of his own Guards to back divers Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talions,<note place="margin">Makes a new at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt on <hi>Pene.</hi>
               </note> which by the favour of the Canon and the hedges, were to open the way for him to come to the ſecond River, on the other ſide of which the French Army was encamp'd.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Why Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur accepts the battel.</note>Monſieur, who obſerved all theſe motions, was in a great impatience to come to handy ſtrokes, not ſo much in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of his own glory, and for the advantage that would thereby accrue to his Majeſty. He very well foreſaw that if the Prince were contented to make headagainſt them without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging in a Battel, he might
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:29680:56"/>
ſo ſpin out the Time in length, and by that only means render their deſign againſt St. <hi>Omers</hi> unprofitable. He ſaw alſo that he had the diſadvantage of the ground, and the fewer forces, but the forementioned Reaſons made him ſhut his eyes againſt all others, carried on by his own courage, having great confidence in his Troops, who teſtified a very great deſire of doing well. He preſently prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all things as a General that would not refuſe the Combat. He then about nine in the morning oppoſed to the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders who advanced, the two Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talions of <hi>Anjou</hi> right over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Bridge of the River, and gave order that the right wing ſhould guard the Artillery to the ſame place, which play'd upon the Enemies Battel till two a clock in the afternoon. He
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:29680:57"/>
alſo ordered Marſhal <hi>Luxemburg</hi> to retake the Abby of <hi>Pene,</hi> which was on the left ſide where the Marſhal comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. This Poſt was an aſſured paſſage for the Enemies advance, and was of very great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The Marſhal executed that order with the Royal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments and that of the Crown, one Battalion of <hi>Stoppa</hi>'s, the Dragoons of <hi>Liſtenoy</hi> and other Troops,<note place="margin">Pene <hi>reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi>
               </note> and with four pieces of Canon. The Hollanders after a long reſiſtance were compelled to diſlodg, which they did after they had put fire to the place and rendred it unprofita- to either party.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An ill moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Prince.</note>In the mean time his Royal Highneſs underſtood that the enemy had left with the better part of his Army the Height which was on the other ſide of the River of <hi>Pene</hi> with an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:29680:57"/>
deſign to paſs over and to fight. This oblig'd him to ſend away preſently the Chevalier <hi>Clinvilliers</hi> with ſome Officers to take a view more neerly of the front of the enemies Army,<note place="margin">Monſieur views the paſſages.</note> which appeared but weak on the place where they faced the right wing of the French. The Chevalier brought him word that there was in that place a ſtone Bridg, by which they might paſs over, for that it was not guarded at all, and that he had ſeen on the other ſide of that Bridg ſome Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons ſuſtained by Battalions ill drawn up and eaſie to be broken. This movement of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the Condition of theſe Troops offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed too fair an occaſion to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to be neglected; and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur preſently made uſe of it.</p>
            <p>His Army had changed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:29680:58"/>
the Order of battel by theſe movements; as alſo by the diſpoſition of the Ground and the occaſion that had engaged him to it, ſome of the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons on the Right having paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over to the left, and many Battalions of the ſecond Line being advanced into the firſt. Monſieur did not only make uſe of the Officers of the Army and the Aids <hi>de Camp</hi> to carry Orders and to obſerve the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Armies, but he alſo employed the Gentlemen of his houſe, ſome being order'd to go to divers places, others to ſtay fixed in certain particular poſts, and another part to be about his perſon. The moſt conſiderable of theſe were the Chevalier <hi>de Beuvron</hi> Captain of his Guards, the Marquis <hi>d' Effiat</hi> firſt Eſquire, the Marquis <hi>Pluvault,</hi> the Chevalier <hi>Nanto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villet,</hi>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:29680:58"/>
Monſieur <hi>de Grave</hi> and many others which we ſhall mention hereafter.</p>
            <p>It was about two a Clock in the afternoon when Monſieur who had reſolv'd upon the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note place="margin">M. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mieres</hi> has order to begin the battel.</note> ſent word to Marſhal <hi>d' Humieres</hi> to advance towards the enemies Front, with order to fight if he found a favourable occaſion. The Marſhal having perceived the ſtone Bridg and divers places on the River eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be paſſ'd, he let his Royal Highneſs know by <hi>Chanly</hi> a good Officer of Marſhal <hi>de Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis,</hi> and who very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the buſineſs of war, that he thought good to ſend the Dragoons of the Collonel Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral which he had ranged, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the fight, for that there could not be offer'd a better opportunity. In paſſing the River he preſented himſelf before the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:29680:59"/>
left wing of the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> having with him the <hi>Gens d' Armerie</hi> and the Kings Musketeers, having order'd to follow him two Battalions of <hi>Navar</hi> with a deſign to gain the height and the Gardens in the middle of the enemies firſt Line. He fell immediatly within two groſs Battalions of Hollanders,<note place="margin">A dangerous buſineſs.</note> ſeconded by nine Squadrons of <hi>Brederodes, Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kell</hi> and others. To diſintangle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from them he commanded the two Battalions of <hi>Navar</hi> and the Musketeers to attacque them,<note place="margin">The valour of the muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keteers.</note> making the later to a light. When the Hollanders ſaw before them the Red-coats, for ſo they called the Musketeers, they heard the commander of the Battalion of <hi>Oalkembourg</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate his ſoldiers to ſuſtain manfully but that ſhock, and the Victory ſhould be eaſily
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:29680:59"/>
theirs afterwards. But neither the perſwaſion of the enemies Officers nor the Tempeſt of two vollies of their Muskets, which they anſwered with their piſtols, could hinder theſe Musketeers from overthrowing by dint of Sword the Regiment which oppoſed them, whilſt thoſe of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>var</hi> routed the other. After the defeat of theſe foot the Muske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers ſeeing the Horſe coming towards them, which back'd them, returned to mount their Horſes with ſo great precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for fear of looſing the opportunity of charging, that Chevalier <hi>Sourdis</hi> and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers and Troops which followed them imagined that they had been beaten back, which cauſed the Chevalier <hi>Sourdis</hi> to ſay to them that they ſhould not preſs ſo, as to cauſe thoſe that were advancing to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:29680:60"/>
believe they were routed. The Marſhal ſeeing the Enemies Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons to advance after the rout of their two Battalions, he oppoſed them with the Marquis <hi>de Livourn</hi> with the <hi>Gens d' Armery,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had endured the brunt of two diſcharges, at the noſe of the muskets, with their ſwords in their hands paſſed over the bodies of all theſe of the firſt Line. But being willing to puſh on the victory farther, it was impoſſible for him to make them keep their Ranks in the heat of the Combate, ſo that the Enemies Squadrons falling on a ſudden upon them, put them into diſorder. But <hi>Revel</hi> with his Brigade ſuccour'd them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opportunely, giving them the means to put themſelves into a Body, and to divers others of his Troops to advance as far as a great ſpace where there were
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:29680:60"/>
yet two Battalions ſuſtained by all the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. In the mean time <hi>Cardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier</hi> advertiſed the Marſhal that they ſaw above fifteen Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons to deſcend from the hill,<note place="margin">The hazard of Marſhal <hi>Humieres.</hi>
               </note> who were coming to fall upon the flank of his wing, who or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the ſame <hi>Cardonnier</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General to make head againſt them with the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of <hi>Coniſmark,</hi> and the Chevalier <hi>de Sourdis</hi> to bring on the Musketeers who had reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their horſes.</p>
            <p>It was then that Monſieur began to engage himſelf on his ſide.<note place="margin">Monſieur en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages.</note> He cauſed the Infantry to advance, and ordered Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal <hi>Luxemburg</hi> to cauſe his leſt wing to advance.</p>
            <p>Marſhal <hi>Humieres</hi> was ſtill in all the dangers and perils,<note place="margin">M. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mieres</hi> beats the Enemy.</note> finding new obſtacles. The two Battalions which were in the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:29680:61"/>
great ſpace, one of which was the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> Guards, ſtanding firm before the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of Curaſiers and of <hi>Tilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det,</hi> and could not be broken without the Infantry. He then commanded <hi>Crevaut</hi> with the Queens Battalions, and <hi>Deſbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> and <hi>Raouſſet</hi> with thoſe of <hi>Navar</hi> to chace them, which was executed after a moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous reſiſtance. Having put to flight thoſe Battalions, he met within a large plain all the Enemies Cavalry who had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared themſelves for to receive him, there being among others one Squadron of white Horſe of the Princes own Guard, and for that <hi>Revel</hi>'s Brigade had ſuffer'd much, he cauſed the <hi>Gens d' Armerie</hi> to advance, who being rallied and having liberty to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend themſelves on every ſide, they began to charge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:29680:61"/>Monſieur who was in the midſt of it,<note place="margin">Monſieur en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages thoſe that fly to return to fight.</note> ſeeing ſome Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, and ſome Squadrons fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before a great Body of the Enemies Foot in the ſame place where he begun to fight he ran to them crying. <hi>Do you ſee me, and fly? where is the honour of</hi> France?<note place="margin">By his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and Valour.</note> At the ſame time he made the Battalions of <hi>Greeder</hi> and <hi>Phiffer</hi> to march, to which he joyned his own company of the Guards, and kept none about his perſon but his Gentlemen and Domeſticks. After theſe orders he rallied thoſe that fled, and ſent them back to the fight, encouraging them by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and overthrew all the Enemies Infantry, who having prevailed in the diſorder of the French, had almoſt took their Camp. Monſieur expoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf very much in this occaſion, receiving one Shot from a Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:29680:62"/>
upon his Arms. The Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the front,<note place="margin">The Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> and divers other Gentlemen and Domeſticks belonging to his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs were wounded by his ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">M. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miers</hi> knows that Monſieur is victorious.</note>Marſhal <hi>de Humieres</hi> ſeeing at the diſorder of the Enemies In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry, very well perceiv'd that Monſieur had gotten ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable advantage. And find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he had nothing to fear on that ſide, and having aſſured himſelf on the other ſide with the Brigade of <hi>Moutrevel</hi> of the ſecond Line, which was in very good order, he reinforced the <hi>Gens d' Armery</hi> once more which had ſuffer'd much, with the Brigade of <hi>Revel</hi> and other Squadrons which were neer it,<note place="margin">Puts the left wing of the Hollanders to the rout.</note> and charged the groſs body of the Hollanders Cavalry, which after an obſtinate fight began at
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:29680:62"/>
laſt to repaſs the River, and then to disband and fly. Monſieur at the ſame time was ready with his Infantry on the left ſide of that victorious Wing, and met the Marſhal who came from conquering with the Cavalry the left wing of the Enemies, where were their greateſt forces, and where fortune ſeemed to diſpute with the bravery of his Troops.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> who with his left wing had not found that reſiſtance in the Enemies right, and who had wholly broken them, had order from his Royal Highneſs to purſue the victory with divers Squadrons of the Collonel Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals and ſome others, who were drawn from the right wing of Marſhal <hi>d' Humieres,</hi> and which the Count <hi>Pleſſis</hi> had the charge to conduct to him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:29680:63"/>
               <note place="margin">The dangers and bravery of the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
               </note>The Hollanders Army in the confuſion gained the height and the way to <hi>Caſſel</hi> and <hi>la Belle.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> after that he had expoſed himſelf divers times, and had received ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſhots upon his Arms, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Battel loſt without reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very retired after all his cares ſad and followed by few peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, hardly knowing whither to go. He went firſt to <hi>Steenwood</hi> and thence to <hi>Poperinghen,</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at this time that fortune was not anſwerable to his courage.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Monſieurs march.</note>Monſieur advanced as far as the hill, which was on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of the ſecond River, with the Brigades of <hi>d' Auba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode</hi> and <hi>Villechauvis</hi> to ſtay for the Marſhal of <hi>Luxembourg,</hi> or to ſuſtain him in caſe that Count <hi>Naſſau</hi> ſhould have attaqued him with thoſe Troops which he led. The Marſhal ſcattered
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:29680:63"/>
many of the Troops who had rallied to ſave their Baggage,<note place="margin">Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgs <hi>Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions.</hi>
               </note> and took many Officers and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers priſoners, even two leagues on the other ſide <hi>Caſſel.</hi> The Hollanders loſt all their Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, Food, and Priſoners,<note place="margin">The Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders loſs.</note> thirteen pieces of Canon, a great many Mortarpieces, fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Standards, one and forty Enſigns and above ten thouſand men, that is to ſay 3000 ſlain, as many wounded or taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and the reſt run away or rendred incapable of ſervice.</p>
            <p>The chief of quality that were there loſt of the Hollanders were <hi>Walſtein</hi> Commander of his Highneſſes Dragoons.<note place="margin">Hollanders of quality ſlain.</note> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels <hi>Scaep, Arembergh, Greames, Grime, Holfwege, Hornby, Truxes,</hi> Majors of <hi>Brederods</hi> Foot, <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck, Klooſtet</hi> the eldeſt ſon of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Kilpatrick</hi> Governour of <hi>Boſleduc, Everwyn</hi> Lieut. Col. of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:29680:64"/>
the ſame Regiment. Collonel <hi>Slaneberg,</hi> the Baron of <hi>Lotthen</hi> and 150 Officers more.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Wounded and priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note>Thoſe that were wounded and taken priſoners were <hi>Ryſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with</hi> Cornet of the Guards of the Body, <hi>Hortman</hi> Lieutenant of the Cavalry of <hi>Valdek, Croon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main</hi> Lieutenant Colonel of the Guards, <hi>Siber</hi> Major, <hi>Laer</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, <hi>la Noy</hi> Lieutenant Collonel to Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> and Major <hi>Salis</hi> Lieutenant Collonel of <hi>Holſtein</hi> with the Major of the ſame Regiment, <hi>Haude</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Collonel of <hi>Horn</hi> with two Captains, <hi>Schaep</hi> Major of <hi>Girickel,</hi> the Count <hi>Warfuſce</hi> and Collonel <hi>Vergne</hi> wounded, and priſoner, as alſo Collonel <hi>Witttenhoue,</hi> Lieutenant Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Oalkemburg,</hi> Collonel the Count of <hi>Lippe, Poeduvel</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Collonel of the <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgs,</hi> Major <hi>Grime,</hi> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:29680:64"/>
Collonel <hi>Zobel,</hi> Collonel <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regnault</hi> wounded, and about an 100 others as well Chief as under Officers.</p>
            <p>The defeat of this Army had been entire but for the inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Ground, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, the Hedges, the Forreſts, the Shrubs and the coming on of the night.</p>
            <p>The Troops of the enemies that behaved themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markuably were among the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry thoſe of the Regiments of the Life Guard and the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons of his Highneſs,<note place="margin">The Troops that did well.</note> thoſe of <hi>Valdek, Brederods, Kinſkel, Skaep Krouemburg, Aremberg, Greams</hi> being Scotch. Among the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, the Regiments of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Guard of Foot, that of Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Hoſteins,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgs, Courland, Ringrave, Waldeck, Horne, Girikil, Van-Eppe,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:29680:65"/>
Lavergne, Kilpatrick, Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenhove, Oalkembourg, Tourſay, Lippe, Klooſter, Grime, Hoffwege, Zobel, Albrunſvart, Slaugembur</hi> and three of <hi>Zeland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Victory coſt Monſieur about two thouſand men kill'd or wounded and ſome priſoners.<note place="margin">Slain and wounded of the French.</note> Among thoſe that were ſlain were <hi>Moiſſac</hi> Cornet of the Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keteers <hi>l' Grange</hi> Cornet of the Scotch <hi>Gens d' Armes Maker</hi> Cornet of the Engliſh, <hi>Boſſier</hi> Captain of the Guards, the Chevalier <hi>Beauveaux</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Lieutenant of Monſieurs <hi>Gens d' Armes,</hi> the Marquis of <hi>Villaſerre,</hi> and <hi>Beneſe</hi> Captains of <hi>Tilladet, l' Eſtoille</hi> Captain under the Marſhal <hi>Logis</hi> of the <hi>Dauphins</hi> Dragoons, <hi>Mardoliers, Tlei</hi> and <hi>Villairs</hi> Captains of <hi>Burgundy, Sebaſtier</hi> Captain in the Queens Regiment, <hi>Crean, Humiers</hi> Lieutenant Colonel,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:29680:65"/>
               <hi>Sigoville</hi> Major and <hi>Gozon</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in the Regiment of <hi>Le Main. Du Chelar</hi> Major, <hi>Lantil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lac</hi> and <hi>Meschatin</hi> Captains in that of <hi>Anjou, Briſſet</hi> Captain in that of <hi>Geneva</hi> a <hi>Peimontois. Villars</hi> Lieutenant Collonel in the Royal Italian Regiment. <hi>Piequemont</hi> Colonel of the Regiment of Walloons. The Chevalier <hi>Silly</hi> a Gentleman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to his Royal Highneſs.</p>
            <p>Priſoners, Count <hi>Carces</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. in the Scotch <hi>Gens d' Armes</hi> dyed of his wounds. The Chevalier <hi>La Guetle</hi> Captain Lieutenant of the Engliſh alſo wounded, <hi>Refuge</hi> Captain and <hi>Bourru</hi> Lieutenant of the Guards.</p>
            <p>Wounded: the Marquis of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourn,</hi> the Count <hi>de Luc</hi> Muske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teer. In the Scotch <hi>Gens d' Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merie Livry</hi> and <hi>Paſſage,</hi> Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termaſters. In the Engliſh, the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:29680:66"/>
Chevalier <hi>Eſtoges</hi> under Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, The Chevalier <hi>Crolly</hi> Enſign, <hi>Obrieu</hi> Quartermaſter. In the <hi>Gens d' Armery</hi> of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy</hi> the Marquis of <hi>Montgon</hi> under Lieutenant. In that of <hi>Flanders</hi> two Quartermaſters and one Brigadier. In the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Queens Light horſe, the Marquis <hi>Sequille</hi> Captain Lieutenant. In that of the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins</hi> light Horſe the Marquis <hi>Vallarceaux</hi> under Lieutenant. In that of the <hi>Gens d' Armerie</hi> of <hi>Anjou Lanion</hi> under Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. In that of the Collonel Generals Captain <hi>Blot.</hi> In that of the Campmaſter General the Chevalier <hi>Luſſau</hi> Captain, and <hi>Ferriers</hi> Cornet. In that of the Curaſſiers <hi>Mouces</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. In that of <hi>Tilladets Catin</hi> Aid Major and the Chevalier <hi>Narbonne</hi> Captain. In that of <hi>Sourdis Caille</hi> Captain. In that
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:29680:66"/>
of the Dragoons Collonel Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Paynae, Chemin, Grand-Val,</hi> and <hi>Cuſſan</hi> Captain. In that of <hi>Liſtenoy Baudet; Lajanie</hi> and <hi>La Font</hi> Captains. In that of the French Guards <hi>Maliſſey</hi> and other Captains, <hi>Sage, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennes</hi> and <hi>Fouilles</hi> Lieutenants, <hi>Jolley, Beaumont</hi> under Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, and <hi>Nonaut</hi> Enſign. In that of <hi>Navar Lurcy, Boiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roux, Caſtillon, Harlier, Denot</hi> and <hi>Riotot</hi> Captains. In the Royal Regiment <hi>Villechauve</hi> Lieutenant Collonel and Briga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of the Infantry, <hi>Biſeiux</hi> and <hi>Valle-ſablon</hi> Captains. In that of <hi>Conty</hi> the Chevalier <hi>Friſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinet, Marvel</hi> and St. <hi>Seve</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains. In that of <hi>Burgundy</hi> the Chevalier <hi>Villairs, Talleures,</hi> St. <hi>Cloy, Beaureguard</hi> and <hi>Thomaſſin</hi> Captains. In the Queens Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Farges</hi> Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, <hi>Grimpier, Val Croſſeau, Duval,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:29680:67"/>
Montgrain</hi> and <hi>Bonnet</hi> Captains. In that of <hi>Vaiſſeaux Lauzier</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, <hi>La Tournelle, Boiſſiere, Arbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville, La Mare</hi> and <hi>Renoir</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains. In that of <hi>Lyonois L' Eſtolle</hi> Lieutenant Colonel, <hi>Sercave, Dapinat, Bellegard, Montbriſon, L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntival, Montagny, d' Enonom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> and <hi>Bony</hi> Captains. In that of <hi>Humieres Dames</hi> Major, <hi>Codere, Francalliere, Moncabau, Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, L' Hoſpital. Normandy La Seine, Milon</hi> and <hi>Goſſe</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains. In that of <hi>La Maceyns de La Haye de La Motte</hi> and <hi>du Tiel</hi> Captains. In that of <hi>Anjou Melonnier</hi> Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Deſnac, Clerac, Boulay, Boulac, Scal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg, Chautezerce, Ferriere, Palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, Du Long</hi> and <hi>Le Comte</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains. In that of the Crown the Chevalier <hi>Betancourt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> Colonel, <hi>Servey,</hi> and the Marquis of <hi>Aire</hi> the eldeſt ſon of the Count <hi>Tavanes</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:29680:67"/>
In the <hi>Genevian Piemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tois du Clos,</hi> St. <hi>Luce, Choſil, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tovet</hi> and St. <hi>Seriel</hi> Captains. In the Royal Italian Regiment the Count of <hi>Serraville</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>Orſucci,</hi> and <hi>Roſſa</hi> Captains. <hi>Griffi, Surgilli, Validini; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chetti</hi> and <hi>Buzzoni</hi> under Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. In that of <hi>Phiffer Borgilli Margdoſſi</hi> and <hi>Aet</hi> Captains. In that of <hi>Greeders Zegber</hi> Major, <hi>Fabri, Courtent, Burent</hi> and <hi>Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teville</hi> Captains.<note place="margin">Volunteers who ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> that of <hi>Stoup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe Benſelle</hi> Captain, and ſome of the under Officers of each Regiment.</p>
            <p>There were beſide very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons of Quallity who on this occaſion ſignalized them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the quality of Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers, as the Prince of <hi>Iſenghin;</hi> the Brother of the Count <hi>de Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> the Marquis of <hi>Thury, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranantum, La Vallerie</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemen of the French
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:29680:68"/>
               <hi>Flanders.</hi> Monſieur St. <hi>Poüange,</hi> known very well for his employ which he diſpenſed with to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf to the peril and dangers of War, not failing by by an exceſs of zeal and courage to be in the firſt of the Troops that fought, and did great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in retaining thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be diſordered and in ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying thoſe again who were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">This is the third Battel ſtruck in this place.</note>The heat of the fight laſted three hours and an half, that is to ſay from two a clock in the afternoon to half an hour after five in the evening. This is the third Battel which hath been ſtruck under <hi>Caſſel</hi> by three Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals bearing the names of <hi>Philip.</hi> The firſt was advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to the low Countries through the ill fortune of <hi>Philip</hi> the Fair, but the other two were as glorious to <hi>France</hi> through
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:29680:68"/>
the courage of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Valois,</hi> and throgh the valour of this <hi>Philip</hi> Duke of <hi>Orleans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The news of this Victory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing publiſhed in the Camp of the King, it was ſolemniſed by three vallies of all the Canon and all the Musketeers. His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty giving to the Marquis <hi>d' Effiaut</hi> a Diamond worth two thouſand Piſtoles,<note place="margin">The King ſends to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement Monſieur.</note> and ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Monſieur <hi>de Geſvres</hi> the chief Gentleman of his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to the Monſieur to teſtifie his Joy.<note place="margin">The news in <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Merille</hi> chief Groom of the Chamber to his Royal Highneſs brought this welcome news to Madame on the twelfth at night. The next day Monſieur the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi> accompanied with the Princes of <hi>Conty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Madame complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> the Duke of <hi>Montauſier</hi> his Governour and many other young Princes and Lords of the Court, came from
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:29680:69"/>
the Caſtle of St <hi>Germains</hi> to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> to rejoyce with her for the proſperous ſucceſs of the Kings Arms under the conduct of Monſieur. His Majeſty wrote to her and ſent Monſieur <hi>de Gombaud</hi> one of his Gentlemen in ordinary to compliment her, and all the Princes and Princeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Blood, Miniſters, Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and the chief perſons of the Realm came to teſtifie their Joy to that Princeſs. They made Bonfires for joy before the Palace Royal and alſo thorow all <hi>Paris</hi> by the people.<note place="margin">Rejoycing.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Citta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray is</hi> preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note>After this victory they began to preſs upon the Cittadel of <hi>Cambray.</hi> From the thirteenth to the fourteenth at night they enlarged the places for their Arms, and their Lodgment to put their Artillery under covert, and the deſcent into the ditch. They raiſed new Batteries and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:29680:69"/>
ſprung ſome mines, and they prepared and charged others.</p>
            <p>The fourteenth in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Duke of <hi>Villeroy</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General, being on the Guard with <hi>Rubentel</hi> Brigadier of the Infantry, and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>d' Angeau</hi> Aid <hi>de Camp,</hi> two Battalions of the <hi>Dauphins</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an attaque on the plain and of the Kings Battalions from without the Town,<note place="margin">An Half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moon taken and reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> they took the halfmoon being on the left hand being wholly ruined by the Canon. The Governour of the Cittadel not being able to ſuffer them ſo to carry it at noon day, knowing of what conſequence it was in giving courage to the French by ſuch eaſie ſucceſs, he detached ſome of the beſt Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Soldiers, and made them retake it before the French had begun to make any Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The ſame Soldiers being
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:29680:70"/>
willing to continue their poynt, and to proceed to overthrow their Works, the Duke of <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy</hi> repulſed them vigorouſly and had almoſt retaken the half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moon if they had had any Tools and Workmen to have lodged there, and if they had not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that they had attaqued it more out of an Importment of Bravery than out of any reaſon of War.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</note>From the fifteenth to the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth the Count St. <hi>Geran,</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Camp, Joſſeaux</hi> Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadier and the Marquis <hi>Chiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> Aid <hi>de Camp,</hi> being on the Guard of the Trench, with two Battalions of <hi>Picardy,</hi> they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried entirely the ſame Fort, and there made their Lodgments, whilſt that two Battalions of the Guards guarded the works on the right hand. His Majeſty had ordered St. <hi>Geran</hi> not to be
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:29680:70"/>
too wilful in the taking it, in caſe that he ſhould find any great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, for that poſt being on the left ſide and without the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taques, the taking of it appeared unprofitable and he had a mind to preſerve his Soldiers. But the out Centinels, and the ſmall Guards being on the point of the Halfmoon, at the only menaces which a Serjeant of <hi>Picardy</hi> made ſomething boldly, they which guarded the place aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned it.</p>
            <p>The ſixteenth the Marſhal <hi>Feuillade</hi> being in the Trench with the Marquis of <hi>Cavois</hi> Aid <hi>de Camp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned.</note> the King commanded a ceſſation of Arms, and let the Governour underſtand by the Chevalier <hi>Nogent</hi> Aid <hi>de Camp,</hi> alſo to the King, that he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the place according to all the Laws of War, and that could be expected from a man of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:29680:71"/>
and reputation; that the Army from which he might have expected relief was wholly defeated without hope of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting together again, that the halfmoons and all the out places were taken, that there had been many breaches made, and mines ſprung to enlarge them, and in concluſion he ought not to be wilful in any longer defence of the place, which would only ſerve to deſtroy a great many valiant men on either ſide, which he might avoid, whilſt he was in a condition to make an honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and advantagious Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His anſwer.</note>The Governour anſwered by a letter ſent back by the ſame Chevalier <hi>Nogent,</hi> that he was yet in a condition to defend the place, that when his mines ſhould have ruined thoſe Baſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they would attaque, there
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:29680:71"/>
was ſtill one where he could lodg himſelf in ſafety, and that at laſt when he ſhould be forced to yield to his power, he hoped that his Majeſty would uſe his ordinary generoſity towards thoſe Soldiers which had done but their duty.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs on the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth in the morning ſeeing two Baſtions almoſt overthrown by the mines and by the Canon, their beſt Halfmoons loſt, the the ditches wholly filled up, and guard in the Trench in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to give a general Aſſault, he thought it no part of his duty to ſtay for it, and more to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to preſerve for his party the the reſt of the Gariſon, and ſome riches, which he ſaw very well could not be ſaved but by a capitulation, knowing as he did the valour of the Beſiegers, and that the victory would be eaſily
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:29680:72"/>
atchieved in the preſence of the King, who knew to come by it through ways ſo ſhort and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing. The King alſo treated him as favourably as he could wiſh. He permitted him and his Gariſon to come forth at the breach with their Arms and Baggage, two pieces of Canon, and guarded as far as <hi>Bruſſels.</hi> His Majeſty immediately ſent Marquis <hi>Louvis</hi> into the Citta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del. The Governour preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf to the King ſick and wounded, who praiſed his brave carriage in the defence of the place. The Garriſon went forth in good condition, except the Iriſh Regiments of <hi>Molem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> and <hi>Tilly,</hi> who as they had performed the moſt vigorous Actions, had been alſo the moſt ill treated.</p>
            <p>The King then cauſed <hi>Te De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> to be ſung in the Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:29680:72"/>
Church,<note place="margin">The King enters the Town and gives thanks.</note> and as if Heaven would concur with Earth to fill up the meaſure of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs proſperity, the Siege was finiſh'd the ſame day that his Majeſty had finiſhed in his Camp the ſtations of the Grand Jubilee. The Archbiſhop of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> and the Father <hi>de La Chaiſe</hi> Confeſſer to the King, upon the Queſtion which had been form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whether his Majeſty could obtain the Jubilee in any other place than that which was ſet down in the Bull, decided that there was no place limited for the perſon of his Majeſty, ſince he was not in the ſame Capacity as ſimple Travellers.</p>
            <p>Lent alſo was concluded at the ſame time, which was now a time of mortification to the Confederates as well as to the Catholiques.<note place="margin">And diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments.</note> The King gave the Government of <hi>Cambray</hi>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:29680:73"/>
to <hi>Cezan</hi> Major of the Regiment of Guards, the Lieutenancy to <hi>Dreux,</hi> the Majorality to <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſot</hi> Engineer, the Command of the Cittadel to <hi>Choiſi</hi> one of the cheif Engineers, and the Lieuten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ancy to <hi>du Freſne.</hi> And for that <hi>Cezan</hi> was Governour of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi> that Government was given to <hi>Lerretiere.</hi> The King then gave order for to repair the Breaches, and to raiſe up the walls both of the Village and of the Cittadel, to put the fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in a good Condition, and to fling down their works.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The news carried to <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </note>The King ſent away Count <hi>Grammount</hi> to carry the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come news to the Queen and to the <hi>Dauphin.</hi> The twenty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung in <hi>Paris</hi> in the Church of <hi>Noſtredame</hi> The Queen and the <hi>Dauphin</hi> accompanied with the Prince and Princeſſes and Ambaſſadors
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:29680:73"/>
of Sovereign Princes, that were uſed to aſſiſt there; being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and Bonfires were made at night thorow the whole Town.<note place="margin">The Queen ſends to complement the King and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur.</note> The Queen ſent to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie her joy to the King firſt; and to Monſieur, for the proſperity of this Campagne by the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Nantia</hi> her Eſquire in ordinary.</p>
            <p>The King departed from <hi>Cambray</hi> on the twentieth in the morning;<note place="margin">The Kings departure.</note> paſſing through <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chain</hi> and lay at <hi>Douay.</hi> The twenty firſt he went to <hi>Lens</hi> and lay at night at <hi>Bethune.</hi> The twenty ſecond he went to <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouanne,</hi> whither Monſieur came to ſee his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Monſieur after the Victory againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ſtayed ſome days in his poſt,<note place="margin">Monſieurs Actions af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel.</note> as well to obſerve the condition of the Enemies Army, as to hinder any of thoſe Troops from get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:29680:74"/>
into St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and alſo to give time for his Cavalry to take the benefit of the Forrage which they had found on the other ſide of <hi>Caſſell,</hi> and for his Infantry to make uſe of the proviſions which the Hollanders had abandoned, and was enough to ſerve his Army for ten days at leaſt. His Royal Highneſs ſent preſently into the Feild where the Battel was ſtruck, Carts and other Carriages with Phyſitians Chirurgians and neceſſary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions to ſuccour thoſe Enemies who had need of it, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded no difference to be made at that time, betwixt thoſe unfortunate people and thoſe of his own Men. Monſieur did not fail to preſs on the Siege in the mean time. Every day four Battalions and ſome Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons had order to enter the Trenches and to attack the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:29680:74"/>
Cow-fort.<note place="margin">A Sally.</note> On the tenth of <hi>April</hi> the Beſieged perceiving that Monſieur had quitted the Siege to meet with the Hollanders Army, they reſolved to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to retake that Fort by a brisk and vigourous Sally which they made. But the Marquis <hi>La Trouſſe</hi> who was upon the Guards gave them a repulſe. Afterwards in the Quarter of <hi>du Bac</hi> and of <hi>Nieurlet,</hi> where <hi>Phif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> commanded, they intercept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Letters which the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour and the Magiſtrates of St. <hi>Omers</hi> wrote to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> which contained the ſad eſtate they were in, being as yet ignorant of the defeat given to the Prince. Monſieur cauſed a coppy of them to be taken to ſhew to the King, and thought it convenient to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the original to paſs, that the enemy might be informed
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:29680:75"/>
of their ſtraits.<note place="margin">A new Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</note> His Royal Highneſs cauſed the Artillery to be advanced againſt St. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> and raiſed a new Battery of twenty pieces of Canon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the High Bridge. The At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacque of <hi>Tattinghen</hi> being left the ſame inſtant that Monſieur quitted his quarters, for that he found he had not forces enough to keep that poſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> de Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mieres <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns.</hi>
               </note> but Marſhal <hi>de Humieres</hi> returned before the place to put all things in a condition to redouble the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacques. The Beſieged frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſallied forth, taking ſeveral priſoners. On the ſeventeeth they made one in which <hi>Cardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niere</hi> was wounded, <hi>Frezelier</hi> the ſon killed, and a good num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Soldiers; but all thoſe endeavours of the Beſieged, how brisk ſoever they were, were but like the laſt glimmering of a Lamp going out. For in fine
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:29680:75"/>
Monſieur having given his Army a refreſhment and time to get in the forrage and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the enemies, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> with the reliques of his Army was retreated between <hi>Bruges</hi> and <hi>Gaunt,</hi> returned into the Camp at <hi>Blandeck</hi> on the nineteenth and put the greateſt parts of his Troops in <hi>Battalia</hi> on the Hill of <hi>Arques.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Monſieur re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to the Camp.</note>
            </p>
            <p>On the twentieth at night the Prince <hi>de Robeck</hi> and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of the Town not being able longer to reſiſt the Artillery being now no longer ignorant of the loſs of the Battel, deſpaired of being ſuccoured, apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Conſequence of a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſault and believing they had done all things that Honour required of them for the defence of the place,<note place="margin">The Town capitulates.</note> they demanded to capitulate. Hoſtages were giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:29680:76"/>
on either ſide.<note place="margin">Surrenders it ſelf.</note> Monſieur ſent Collonel <hi>Villars</hi> into the Town and the Spaniards ſents into the Camp Collonel <hi>de Fey</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel of Foot and <hi>d' Harnon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court</hi> Collonel of Horſe. They had yet one Counterſcarp left, one large ditch, and one Rampart of Earth furniſhed with Gabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Stakes and quick Hedges; ſo that they might have been able to hold out for ſome days longer; but ſeeing themſelves without any hope of relief, and being threatned that they ſhould have no quarter if the Town ſhould be taken by aſſault, or be made priſoners of war, if they ſhould defer the time longer ere they rendred themſelves, were perſwaded to come to a concluſion, and which they muſt be forced to do within a few days at the leaſt, and alſo find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the French were not
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:29680:76"/>
at all moved by their long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, hoping thereby at laſt to deſtroy the Troops of that Gariſon, which would be a great loſt to <hi>Flanders,</hi> and which might yet render them good ſervice. All theſe things conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered made them reſolve to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulate. Their demands were ſtrongly debated, and they were reſolved not to receive them but as Priſoners of war; but Monſieur having ſeen the King on the twenty ſecond at <hi>Terouanne,</hi> return'd to his Camp with orders to agree to their Capitulation upon honorable Terms. They left the place with Arms and Baggage, two pieces of Canon and a Guard as far as <hi>Ypres</hi> and <hi>Gaunt.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Robeck</hi> and the Count of St. <hi>Vignant</hi> at the head of their Gariſon made their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to his Royal Highneſs,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:29680:77"/>
who received them with much Civility.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Monſieur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enters the Town.</note>Monſieur entering into the Town cauſed the <hi>Te Deum</hi> to be ſung, viſited the Rampart, and having given the neceſſary Orders for the putting the place into a good Condition, and alſo provided for the neceſſities of the priſoners and for thoſe that were wounded, he went to joyn himſelf to the King.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment dispoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of by the King.</note>His Majeſty had given the Government of the place before he had left his Camp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Cambray</hi> in the Favour of the Marquis St. <hi>Genles</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of <hi>Douay</hi> and gave the Lieutenancy to <hi>Raouſſet</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>Navar,</hi> and made <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chepierre</hi> Engineer the Major, and the command of <hi>Douay</hi> to the Marquis <hi>Pierrefit</hi> an ancient Chevalier of <hi>Lorraine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath been a Cuſtome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:29680:77"/>
the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Complements betwixt the King of <hi>England</hi> and the French King.</note> when there has been amity betwixt them, that when ever either of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches neer each others Coaſt, to ſend mutual Complements each to other. The <hi>French</hi> King therefore ſent to his Majeſty of great <hi>Britain</hi> the Duke <hi>de Crequi</hi> Peer of <hi>France</hi> Firſt Gentleman of his Chamber,<note place="margin">Duke <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui</hi> ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to England.</note> Chevalier of the Orders and Governour of <hi>Paris.</hi> He parted from Court with a Train of above an hundred Gentlemen. The Princes who joyn'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with him to pay their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to their Majeſties of great <hi>Britain</hi> in particular were the Count of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Boüillon</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naco.</hi> The King of <hi>England</hi> ſent into <hi>France</hi> the Earl of <hi>Sunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>York</hi> ſent my Lord <hi>Duras</hi> Captain of his Guards.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:29680:78"/>
               <note place="margin">The King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires peace.</note>The King might probably have encreaſed his Conqueſts by a fourth Siege, and all the low Countries were in ſuch a conſternation, and their Troops in ſo ill an equipage that it was no hard matter for him to have improved his victory, but his Majeſty had a mind to let all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> underſtand that whatever advantage he had got by the continuation of the War, that he had yet a ſtronger inclination for Peace, and in order thereto, he wrot to the King of Great <hi>Britain</hi> as a Mediator, that he was ready to ſign the Articles of Truce, to give leaſure to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the means for a concluſion of Peace. After this the King diſtributed his Troops into their Quarters, breaking in the mean time the courſe of his victories, to let them ſee the diſpoſition which he had to give repoſe to
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:29680:78"/>
               <hi>Europe,</hi> and to put himſelf into a condition to enter upon new enterpriſes, if in caſe the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates ſhould not yield their helping hands to a propoſition ſo reaſonable.</p>
            <p>The King retain'd about his Perſon a part of the Troops of his Horſe,<note place="margin">The King viſits the conquered places.</note> and went to viſit all the places on the Frontiers and his Conqueſts in the low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. He gave to Lieutenant General <hi>Cardonniere</hi> the charge of Camp maſter General of the light Horſe, vacant by the death of the Marquis of <hi>Reynel,</hi> and made a Detachment of ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men under his conduct, for to march on the ſide of the <hi>Meuſe</hi> till further orders. The charge of Commiſſary General, which he had before, was given to the Marquis <hi>Montrevil</hi> Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadier of the Cavalry.</p>
            <p>The twenty fifth his Majeſty<note place="margin">His voyage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:29680:79"/>
came to <hi>Gravelin</hi> and that night to <hi>Dunkirk.</hi> The next day he viſited the Port, Ramparts, and all other places of the Town. The twenty ſeventh he went to <hi>Bergues,</hi> the twenty eighth he returned to <hi>Callis,</hi> where he gave a private Audience to <hi>Griffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> Envoy extraordinary from the Sweed. There he alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the compliments made him from his Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain</hi> and from his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Receives en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voys from <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> by the Earl of <hi>Sunderland</hi> and the Lord <hi>Duras,</hi> who on the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ninth had their Audience of taking leave introduced by Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Bonnevil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mounſieur returns to <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </note>Monſieur having left the King at <hi>Callis,</hi> arrived on the third of <hi>May</hi> at <hi>Paris</hi> with thoſe Gentlemen who followed him. Madame, Madamoſelle and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Princes, Princeſſes,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:29680:79"/>
and great ones of the Realm, came to meet him there and to receive him. The next day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his arrival he went to render his viſit to the Queen in the Covent of the Carmelites in the Street of <hi>Bouloir:</hi> and the fifth he went with all his Family to St. <hi>Germans,</hi> to ſee again the Queen and Monſieur the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin.</hi> The ſame day <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung in the Church of <hi>Noſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame</hi> for the conqueſt of St. <hi>Omer,</hi> and at night Bonfires were made for joy. The Popes <hi>Nuncio</hi> and all the Embaſſadors and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and very many of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of both ſexes made their complements to his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs both for the taking St. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> and for his victory at <hi>Caſſel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Is comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The King having taken a turn about all the Sea places, went into <hi>Artois</hi> with the Court, and ſtaid ſome days at
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:29680:80"/>
St. <hi>Omers.</hi> From thence on the ninth of <hi>May</hi> he made his entrance into <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> and ſtaid a while in the County of <hi>Hainault.</hi> The fourteenth he went to <hi>Conde,</hi> where he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved news of the Sea fight which the Count <hi>d' Eſtree</hi> had gained over the Hollanders in the Port of <hi>Tobago</hi> in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates eſtabliſhed their head quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Country of <hi>Vaes.</hi> They had aſſured themſelves of the Troops of <hi>Oſnabruck, Munſter</hi> and <hi>Newbourg.</hi> The brave Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had projected great enterpriſes, as well with the States General as with the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, and the Confederates in all their marches made appear that they were contriving to revenge themſelves of ſo many affronts they had received by the execution of ſome great deſign.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:29680:80"/>The King rallied all his Troops from their quarters of refreſhment,<note place="margin">The King takes a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of his Troops.</note> the 22th of <hi>May</hi> took a general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of his right wing in the Fields of <hi>Thulin,</hi> and the 23th he review<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his left wing under <hi>Boſſu</hi> in the Territory of <hi>Keeuvrain.</hi> He found his Army more flouriſhing than ever, being about forty Battalions ſtrong and fourſcore and ten Squadrons, not comprehending thoſe Troops which he had detached to reinforce the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Marſhal <hi>Crequi,</hi> nor thoſe which were ſent into the ſervice of the Marſhal <hi>Schomberg</hi> between the <hi>Meuſe</hi> and the <hi>Moſelle.</hi> His Majeſty left the command of thoſe in <hi>Flanders</hi> with Marſhal <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> and went on the 27th thorow <hi>Queſnay,</hi> and the 28th to <hi>Cambray,</hi> the 29 to <hi>Chaune,</hi> the 30th to <hi>Lioncourt</hi> where he was received by the Prince of <hi>Marſillas</hi> the grand Maſter of his Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robe. The 31 in the morning Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur met the King at <hi>Bourget,</hi> and at noon the Queen, the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> and the Princes, and Princeſſes of the Court met his Majeſty at <hi>Clichy,</hi> from whence they went to <hi>Verſailles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third of <hi>June</hi> the Marquis of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:29680:81"/>
               <hi>Siegnelay</hi> preſented to his Majeſty the Meſſieures of Parliament and of the other Sovereign Courts and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Returns and is comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.</note> who did make their ſet Speeches on the felicity of his Arms in that glorious Campain. The fourth Monſieur <hi>Bonnevil</hi> intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to his Majeſty the <hi>Nuncio</hi> and all the Embaſſadors and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Strangers who teſtified their admiration and joy for the ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and greatneſs of his conqueſts.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pain ended in three months.</note>And thus the King ended his Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pain in three months, of which he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed two in his Conqueſts and the other in diſpoſing things to aſſure what he had got. Time will ſhew the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance and conſequences of theſe things better than we can. All that we may ſay, is that after the three moſt conſiderable places in the low Countries both for their repute and fortifications, carried with ſo great promtitude, the hardeſt part of the work was over. By theſe he had co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd all his former conqueſts, and put the frontiers of his Kingdom in a condition to ſuffer no longer from the inroads of thoſe Gariſons, nor to ſuffer any Incommodity from the War.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
